From the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.
Okay, we're rolling around.
Today is Tuesday, September 13, 2011.
My name is Joe Manier of the Southern oral history program at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
I'm with the videographer John Bishop.
We are in St. Augustine, Florida at the Hilton Bayfront Hotel to do some interviews regarding the local movement history.
This is a part of these interviews are being done for the Civil Rights History Project, which is a joint undertaking of the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture and the Library of Congress.
We're delighted in all this effort to have been assisted and are very much looking forward to interviewing Dr. Robert Haillin.
Let me call out that in the room today right now we have an addition myself and John.
We have Mrs. June Conway, Mr. Purcell Conway, our interviewees from left to right.
Mrs. Audrey Nell Edwards Hamilton, and Ms. Joanne Anderson Olmer, and Dr. Haillin is with us as well.
A quick note for the recording. We are not recording on the XD cards.
I think John won't touch a little room, John, so all the 30s. That waits for about 30 seconds.
Okay, I'll take that one so well.
Okay, all of our rallies.
Thank you both so much for sitting down and rolling with our big so flexible this morning as we got this all in motion.
Ms. Hamilton, Ms. Olmer, thanks very much for sitting down with us.
Thank you, Dr. Hill.
I thought I might start with inviting you just to share some reflections of coming up and saying Augustine and maybe a little bit about family and schooling.
That will sort of help us set the stage for how you emerge as activists in your teenage years.
Well, coming up in Synalgusting, Synalgusting to me was a very, very nice, nice town to live in.
To grow up in, we had a lot of black businesses at the time that I grew up.
Washington Street was all remain, street that had a lot of black businesses.
And when we started in the movement, we didn't start off picketing or demonstrating.
We would go down to the St. Paul's AME Church and sit around and just talk about what we were going to do.
You know, that was when school was out.
And when we found out that we had someone, a leader that would back us in a way that we never would have dreamed of.
Because most of the leaders would tell us, no, you can't do that.
That's not the way you do it.
You got to wait.
But Dr. Harvey Haley, he was our advisor, youth advisor.
And he just motivated us to want to go and make a difference in Synalgusting.
Because for me, I didn't too much care about my mom having to come and buy my school supplies at Woodworth.
Because at that time, there was not no Wal-Martin.
It was just a downtown area with Woodworth and Macquarie's.
And they were about our school supplies there.
And there was a lunch counter over there.
And she would go in, come walkin' through the park,
and had to pass the fountain in the park.
Because it had white only on it.
And she would go over there and buy my school supplies.
And she would also buy, you know, little accessories that you needed, you know, for school.
But she couldn't go over and get a drink of water.
I had a problem with that.
And I said to myself, you know, there's something wrong with this picture.
So when I seen the young people gathering up at this church down the street from me,
I saw them go down there and see what they're doing.
But all they were doing was just gathering.
And Mr. Clyde Jenkins, Dr. Helen, Mr. Lucille Plummer, and Miss Fanny Wood, Fuller Wood,
they started bringing up supplies to make picket signs.
So we made our little picket signs and we would go downtown every day.
Every day, every morning, we would meet at St. Paul and get our picket signs
and go to the world, some would go to the Armacurus, and some would go to Woolworth,
some would go to the little local drug stores that was down in the area,
and picket maybe two or three at one place, four or five at another, you know.
And that's how we did it until one day we gathered at St. Paul Church and we said it was in July.
And we said 1963.
1963, July 1963, July 18th.
And we said we were sitting around and we had some old tomatoes,
and we were just sitting there like the name was Jimmy Jackson, Francis Floyd,
and older people, older, older, older, older, older was,
and we were just sitting there, car Williams, and we were just sitting there,
and Francis Floyd said it's time for us to do something.
We got to talk to the doctor.
We got to go and do something.
We got to talk to the doctor and we were talking to him about the sickle of the city,
so big Jimmy Jackson, there's a difference between, there's a little Jimmy Jackson,
and there's a big Jimmy Jackson.
There's a difference between them, and the big Jimmy Jackson said,
well we going down town to city, and go to the city,
I was going to go down town to city,
So we put the signs up against the wall and walked downtown.
We went down to Francis Street, turned down,
watching to the street.
And as we was going down in the little two,
we was in twos, as we was walking down the street,
Mr. Ernest Wells had a barber shop.
And he came out because he was very involved in the NAACP.
And he came out.
He said, where you all think you're going?
We said, we're going to set in.
He said, who told you all the gold set in?
Where's those picket signs?
And we said, we left them at the church.
We going to set in.
He said, well, did Dr. Nol, he didn't?
He said, well, do you have any money?
And we said, no.
And he went back in his barber shop.
He said, you can't buy nothing if you don't have no money.
So he gave, I think it was goldie, goldie, some money.
And he gave big gymma Jackson some money.
So we walked down down.
We never left off a cane street that day.
That was what, one, two, three, three.
It was a service drug store, my cotton is drug store,
and then woodwork.
And we went in goldie in a,
Francis in Jimmy in a, and a,
Gurgine, they went in the service drug store.
And goldie and Harold Jenkins and several more went into my cotton.
Joanne, myself, will a call and say him.
And Dolores and Rosemary and Harris went to woodwork.
And that's where we sat in it.
Would it be OK on Army, the stock, you set the stage so beautifully?
Can I bring in this armor?
And it will bring the worries together.
Yes, go ahead on.
With things really starting.
Yes.
OK.
Thanks, started for me.
I lived on the north side of town.
I lived on the west side.
That means across the track.
And there weren't anything for black children to do
because they didn't have any activities, nothing whatsoever.
So I had to get permission because I had a sister
live on the originale side where the church was two streets
behind Lankanville.
And my mother said, I asked permission,
could I go and participate?
And they, of course, said, yes.
So I went every day over to my sister's house.
And that's how I got hooked up with them.
I would go and say, well, I want
to be involved so I went and I joined.
And that's what happened.
But there was nothing or anything for us to do.
I was going to ask, can you tell me a little bit
about those early meetings of youth council that you joined?
Well, I met Doc.
Doc, you been the one play the piano.
No, no, Janelle.
Janelle, you been the play the piano.
We would have singing.
And we had our little brother, then,
Mr. Was Gerald.
When the Gerald.
He was a brother at that time.
He had a little brother.
For a little while, he was our president, for not long.
For not long.
And we would meet every day and we would go pick it like our
Janelle said.
It was only a few of us, a handful of people that participated
and did that every day.
And after we decided that we wanted to go,
I guess we was tired of just going with the signs.
We wanted to make a difference and just go in and set down
and ask for service.
When you made that decision to, young people made a decision
to go out and do this sit in, you alluded to some
frustration with older leaders who weren't quite so ready
to take more aggressive steps.
Can you talk a little bit about that difference in
perspective between the young folks and older, say,
any of these decisions?
Well, our perspective was that I guess we just wanted to go
on and sit down.
And I guess they wanted a little more time.
Maybe they wanted ready to make that plunge.
But for us, it was like we need to go and sit in and ask
for service.
So that's why we did.
And when we did, we met our adversary who said they do
not serve Niggas here.
You would have to leave, be arrested.
We continue to set.
At the counter, at the counter.
And they said, we tell you if you don't leave, because we
don't serve Niggas here, you will be arrested.
So they called in Elo Davis, which was the sheriff, a big old man.
He showed up and told us the same thing.
We was unlawful guests.
We were undesirable guests.
We was trespassing.
And if we didn't leave, we would be carried to jail.
And that's what happened.
They carried us to jail.
Yes.
And we was also arrested by a black deputy.
Who was named?
DJ Johnson.
Which to me, when he put us in that car,
I think that really was the hurting part of the whole day,
was when he came in and snatched us and told us that we were on the rest.
I would imagine he would have been one of the first black deputies.
Oh, no.
And I just looked because I grew up knowing him, knowing him,
and with the school with his son.
And I looked at him, I'm like, are you really doing this to us?
And he actually not just, he kind of pushed us in the car,
because Elo was there.
And Elo was here.
You know, he had, I guess he was showing up in front of his
mouth.
And they took us to jail.
And we thought we was going to get out.
Or we didn't.
You know, we got in there singing and all.
Or we did.
They hadn't put us in a cell yet.
The group has how many?
It was 16.
16.
And we were just sitting around in the hall like,
and we were singing.
And like I said, I meant those.
We all dependent on Francis Floyd and Jim and Jacob
the oldest ones.
We was kind of leaning on them, you know.
And they were like, don't worry about it.
We're going to get out.
That hell isn't going to leave us in here.
So I'm going to be still OK.
So they came, took Joanne, myself, and Dolores, and Rosemary,
and Harris will call it Sam and locked us up in the men's
part of the jail.
And that's a really goodness.
We wasn't with the other ones.
That's the one where we went with the others.
And the other ones was downstairs.
It was locked up downstairs.
So we was like, I think we heard them
leaving because they were singing.
I said, join the livens.
I said, why were we still in here?
She said, and I said, Rosemary, I said, yo, what's going on?
I said, Francis never leaving.
Oh, there was clapping in the singing and going out to jail.
And there we all locked up until the next morning.
Can I ask you how the experience of actually being
arrested, spending that first night in the jail,
compared to you or young, compared to how you had maybe
imagined it might be, where you, that's a pretty big thing
to happen in the white jail.
Now, but at first, it was fine to us.
We was up there singing.
We had all seven of us.
And we were just clapping and singing.
And it goes, we just knew we were spending the livens.
We know, oh, we just knew that we was
going to get out.
But that didn't happen.
We went to cope the next morning.
And that's when everything spared out of control.
I was going to hold it for you.
Well, just like she said, we was all excited about being locked
up.
We had no sense of fear because we was all together to group.
We were four girls and three boys.
It was seven of us.
So when the judge carried us to court, he had a petition
stating that our parents would sign.
We wouldn't demonstrate anymore until we got to age 21.
And we said, no, don't sign.
But the other two young ladies, parents signed.
So they carried them home.
And another young man, he went home.
So that left Samuel, well, a car,
Ardenel, myself.
OK, now it's joling, trickling down
because we're spending more than two days in jail.
It gets to be one week, two weeks, three weeks, four weeks.
I think the young men was taken in the middle of the morning.
They carried them to Mariana's school.
What, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what,
why did you work things out with your parents
that they didn't sign those points?
See, this is what happened here.
When we were in court and the judge approached us,
and he said to us, he said, I do not want you
all participate in any more demonstrations of any kind.
And we said, no, we, you're not going to do this to us.
And he said, he turned to our parents.
And he said to our parents, I want you
to sign a paper stating that your juvenile kids
will not participate in any more demonstrations of any kind.
Because if Bible Mothers had signed that paper,
they were going to rest after healing.
They were putting them in jail.
They were putting a felony on him.
But what happened was the four of us,
it was a higher power that came upon us
for us to do what we did.
Because this judge was very evil.
He showed it in his voice.
He showed it in the way he acted.
He looked at us.
And when we said no to him, he turned red as a bee
and said, told Ella, you take those commoners
niggles out of here?
Like a monkey.
Like a monkey and throw away the key.
So that's when the NAACP, Mr. Shaw, stood up in front of him
because we didn't have a lawyer at the time.
We had a representative of the NAACP
representing us that day.
And he said to Ella Davis, excuse me, Judge Matthew.
I don't care where you take it.
He's having a take it to a higher code.
He said, I don't care where you take it.
He said, we make the law hell and we break it.
And guess what?
We made that time.
We made it.
He gave us a year.
At least 10 years.
Let me play back for just a second.
Because we can talk about the experience of being
imprisoned for so long or for a formatory school.
Mm-hmm.
Context.
Mr. Haley is a young man now, but he was a very young man then.
And youth chapter leader.
And I wonder if you could talk a little bit about
his leadership style and how he interacted
with the young people in the group
and how you came to know him in that experience.
I met Dr. Haley being involved with the demonstration.
And he always encouraged us to do good, find somebody
that would encourage us to do good things,
and thank good thoughts about ourselves.
So by being there with him, he had a greater influence
on us so that we wouldn't just fool around.
There was nothing to do.
So I thought that was a great thing to do.
Because we wanted to change.
We think we just want to go to the back door all the time.
You want to be able to sit in the front seat like everybody else.
You want to be able to sit to the counter and have
and not go to the window.
You want to sit at the front of the bus and not at the back.
So he encouraged us in that way that we could deserve more.
Everybody deserve the Constitution.
He was a good leader.
Good leader, very good person.
He motivated all of us.
He didn't say, look, we don't want, you know,
good people don't want y'all doing this or just do that.
He motivated, he made us feel, he made us feel like we were doing something right,
that we were doing something right.
And he backed us up 100% in that.
Regardless of whether he gave us his permission to do it,
he still came and stuck by us and said,
I'm with you all.
Regardless, I'm going to be with you all to the end.
Dr. Helen was just like John.
I tell everybody this, like John with Jesus, he never left outside.
And I love him to this day for that.
I will love him to this day for that.
And I love him for being our leader because he was a great leader.
He was a good leader.
And I love him to this day for that because he made a change in our life.
Even though we were with the reform school, it made, still made a difference in our life.
It made a difference in our life because we can say to the world, I am somebody.
All right.
Even though that happened to us when we was 15 and 16, 14,
now we're just like two little ladies, but we still have that driving passion in our heart
for Dr. Helen and for what we did.
We know what we did was right.
That's right.
There was nothing wrong about that.
It's just people with hatred within their heart.
They just, because I always say because God created me brown and you were different color,
it doesn't require for you to have something I can't have.
We're all here and all deserve the same thing.
And another thing that I want to, that has not been said, when we got out of jail, January,
1964, we were out of jail at least three months before Dr. Cain ever came to set out the
scene.
That's what I've been trying to tell Dr. Helen was out everything.
He was out of a leader even to bring Dr. Cain in because Dr. Cain movement did not start
until three months after we were out of jail and we got out of jail January the 23rd,
1964.
It was very much home government.
You know, and he, he, to me, he is the inspiration and the father of Santa Augustine and a little
beyond because really the tale truth if it wasn't for his knowledge and his know how and
his sacrifice because he sacrificed a lot.
I mean a lot for us.
How did you make sense of of as best you can recall thinking back on this, your adolescence,
your 15, 16 years old, how did you make sense of all of the violence and hatred that was exhibited
in the community?
How did you think your way through that?
How did you explain that to yourself or?
I answered and then she came.
I made sense of it because see we had God in our lives and we had spiritual songs that
we sung that uplift us.
You know, the songs that we sung that was uplifting songs and we bypassed the hatred because
before Dr. Ken came we were singing, I love everybody before he even got here, you know.
So we, we was taught by our parents and Dr. Helen that we can overcome but Dr. Violence,
you know, we, the violence was afflicted on us but we did not afflict violence back.
Being locked up for so long and isolation once we arrived at that Reformatory School, we
were 77 days in the county jail.
We were 52 days in isolation at the Reformatory School.
We didn't have nobody but each other to talk to and we had a Bible they gave us but
Spiritsure we was already anointed by the Lord.
That's why I tell people I learned how to pray at the early age.
Right?
You was out doing whatever.
That's all I could do because I was locked up.
Confines and went out your nail for 52 days.
The lady just opened the door early in the morning to get her Bible verse and I used to
sit and look at me, I used to sit in the window, make up songs, see all kinds of things.
But you know, that's why I say it.
They said, I don't know this one.
I said, well you know, I spent all my time but I was in the lock up.
Nobody else don't need to claim that.
I was with you and no you weren't.
I know who I was with for 72 days then for 62 days just locked up.
You know, people don't realize I said, I'm sorry if I say this, I don't mean no.
This is the way I feel.
If we would have had been white children, we would have never, my parents would never
had to suffer.
Maybe in taking in the middle of the morning to a Reformatory School they would never
would have had a suffer 72 days in the county jail.
They would never told my mother you had to sign a petition for your child because she's
coming this in radical.
What she's doing is unconstitutional.
That's what the judge told us.
But I always say it's all right.
We bat at the storm with the help of the Lord and what we was doing was right.
So I just tell people all the time, whatever you do, do what's right because you always
come out in the end right.
And I have to put this in here.
Will a car mother, she was at a bad heart.
A bad heart.
And when the judge sentenced us, she fainted inside the court.
And no matter, and I think about Miss Lour all the time now, no matter how hard
it was on her, she never signed that paper.
And it broke her heart.
She never got over that.
But she never would sign that her son told her mama don't sign it.
She stuck with that.
But it was killing her inside.
And when they took Willa call and Sam away and they came up there that morning to bring
us out breakfast, the pain we heard in Miss Nora and Miss Pryce's voice was unbelievable.
Like I told my mother and Miss Pryce, we heard your pain Miss Pryce and Miss Nora pain.
But joining myself, we seen our mother pain when they came up to that school and seen
our blood and knees.
Scrubbing the floor.
We had the scrub flows on our knees.
We had the wax flows on our knees until you see your face.
If they're not right, you got to go back over it and do it all over again.
That was the state statement.
How well do you think each of you emerged from all of that in the short term?
Did you feel when you finally were released in January that how did you feel in terms of
what that experience had cost you or shown you?
What it did, it showed us that we needed to do more.
So that's what happened.
That's why I was back in jail with Dr. King.
Three months later.
Right.
So though, we still had a lot of work to do.
We can't.
We can't have the same oxygen for here today because both.
We only have two of us.
The two of us.
How long they were incarcerated?
Is that?
They did not share that with us.
They didn't share the experience with us.
Well, I'm going to tell you, me and Willa Carl stayed.
He stayed when I had moved out out west and his mother stayed around the corner from.
And when he came home from the service because he joined the army.
And when he came home his mother would tell him, I can tell you that I live around
the corner.
You better go see her.
And so he said, I have to go see her.
I have to come around here to see you because if I didn't come see you, my mother would
have had a seizure.
And then I asked him.
I said, I sit around and I said, Willa Carl.
I said, You never talked about Maryanna.
I said, You never told me to tell us the story of what happened that night.
You never, you and Sam never said, you know what happened to you all that night when
you all left, left us there, you know, in the jail.
And this is what he said to me.
God risked his soul.
I didn't ask me about Maryanna.
If you ask me about Maryanna I never come see you again.
I said, Are you serious Willa Carl?
He said, I'm serious.
Don't ask me about Maryanna anymore.
So we took it upon ourselves as Sam up in the, so we thought we were going to get us a
story.
And Sam said, We said, That's the dream we're going to ask him.
He's going to have to tell us up here.
He practically told us the same thing.
And I was like, I told you I was trying.
I wonder what happened to Willa Carl at Sam.
What did they do to him?
They had a really, really bad, bad experience that was unbelievable.
They could not talk about it.
Then they would not talk about it.
They took whatever happened to them to the grave.
And I think to this day, I think that had a lot to do with things that happened that
they was going too soon.
That they was counting a lot of pain.
That they didn't want to talk about, like me and Joanne, me and Joanne talked about
it because I was, experience was bad, but it wasn't as bad as we can imagine that we
have found out from other people that Maryanna was doing some terrible things up there
to the young boys.
So we put two and two together and say, our friends suffered for freedom, suffered for
freedom, just for something that they were born with anyway.
They suffered.
You've said a moment ago and we know that soon after you go right back into jail,
right back.
Tell me about how you thought your way back into more direct participation and direct action.
Dr. Haling had Dr. King, and June 1964.
And we went right on back into demonstrating and participating.
First, Dr. Haling.
This is what Dr. Haling sent for the four of us.
And to meet Dr. King.
I'm not sorry if you would please.
Yeah, to meet Dr. King.
And we came, Willikaw, Sam, Joanne, myself and met Dr. King that night.
He was sitting on the couch.
It was a little plastic couch.
Dr. Haling, I remember just a little red couch.
He was in the back.
And Ralph, having that, it was sitting over in a corner.
And Dr. King was sitting in the corner.
And then he had a little hat kicked to the side.
Of course, this is good.
Head is a little hat kicked to the side.
And when we came in, he got up.
And Dr. Haling told him.
He said, well, I know about these four young people.
He said, I want to tell you, I want to hug you all and tell you, you all went beyond
the call of duty.
He said, job well done.
I am so proud of you.
I am so proud.
Even though whatever happened to Sam and Willikaw, they still went back to jail.
Dr. Martha Luther King, SCLC, because we went to jail under the NAACP in 1963.
But went back to jail in 1964 under Southern Christian Leadership Conference.
Dr. King's organization.
I was the one with the jail without the jail.
She went to jail without the King.
I mean, I seem like I was already in the mix of everything.
The stone reason.
I was always in the mix with what happened was, got the King was that.
And at the St. Mary's Church.
And he spoke that night.
And Miss P. Body and Dr. Haling and I, we were in groups.
They all were in groups.
And I was standing up against the, I had no teaching to go in the jail.
I'm not going to lie to you.
I was standing up against the church.
And he turned.
And he stayed me.
And he looked at me and he said, I want my love hero to come and go with me in my group.
I was sitting in my soul.
No, no, no.
I'm honest with you.
I didn't know.
No, not the night.
And I, you can't say no to Dr. King.
So I went to jail.
It was me, Dr. King, Reverend Shillerworth.
And there was a.
I was a young white woman.
I can't recall her name.
But we all went, we all went in, in, in, I don't know who caught was.
But anyway, we all pulled up and went up there.
And I was standing there.
They had my little purse.
I was, we were, we were, at that time I was dressed.
Boy, I tell you.
And a young lady named Diane Mitchell.
And me went up and Dr. King said, we'd be like to, until to be served.
And Brock said, never, did I tell you all I wasn't going to.
Why y'all keep bothering me?
Didn't that, didn't he, did he, did he say, Dr. King?
I let you have a cup of coffee, but the other ones can't come in.
Dr. King said, no, if they can't come in.
I can't come in.
She said, well, I got the call of police and he hollered like the other somebody.
And they said, no, cause, pulling up, pulling us and pulling us, throwing us in the
cause.
No, pulled out the king of the cause of the dog.
And the dog, he was, the dog loved the dog, the king so much he kissed them.
He did, he kissed them.
They don't even have dogs.
And they, they, they, the dog, they, the dogs walking beside us saying, niggas walking.
They was horrible here.
We had some horrible and we never would have thought that the white people here.
We all thought everybody loved one another.
Everybody just got along until we decided that we wanted to integrate and go sit at the
counter.
So they really went completely crazy.
They wanted to kill up all of us.
But you know, going to jail with Dr. King was a good experience that night.
I remember, I remember when we got in jail and him and Ralph Avin Fee and he woke up that
morning and he had told us, cause we was in the cell next to him.
If women's all women's was in the cell next to him.
And he, he said, go morning everybody.
And we said, go morning.
And he said, I want y'all to buy y'all heads and, and prayer and, and, and, and he prayed
and he started singing this song.
I woke up this morning with my mind.
Said, I'm free, I'm woke up this morning with my mind.
Said, I'm free, I'm hallelujah, hallelujah.
And the next thing we know, we heard the, those opening.
He was taking him out, taking him to Jacksonville.
And then that night I got out and Jackie Robinson, hey, came to town.
And I said, well, how those people down the cell, Paul Church, because I lived on Syntron.
That was the name of the people who became MLK.
And they said, oh, Jackie Robinson, the baseball player is speaking down, down there.
So I walked down, down, you couldn't get in, it was packed in there.
You just couldn't get, it was no, no, no, you know, I didn't even stand in the room.
So I was outside sitting on the Catholic church, you know, the, the little stoop out there.
And so somebody came running out the, running out the church hall and, I was, you know,
I was, you know, he's talking about you all, he's talking about you all.
And I'm like, what?
And they were pulling me to, just pulling me to, you know, to him.
And when I got up to him, he just grabbed me and hugged me,
Joanne with a call and say, they were still in jail.
Yeah, how was she?
They were still in the jail.
And, and he just said, oh, I have, I never would have thought that four young people
will be this, have this much courage.
He said, so I'm going to give you and your young friend, Joanne, a relaxing, a relaxing
time at my home in Sanford, Connecticut, to be, I'm flying you there first class.
You didn't know what first class was.
Nothing.
Well, he should have the tickets to Dr. Henry.
Yeah.
We were sitting on the, we were sitting on the bed, Joanne, boy, we were just late.
And the lady came and said, do you all want to look at a movie?
Joanne, let me say, move.
We had never been on a plane and I like it.
Yeah, that's my, that was our first time ever being on a plane.
We were, I said, Joanne, look at that.
We walking out, like the movie star.
We were, we were letting in in New York.
Oh boy, we were just, then he was standing there waiting on us, Jack and Robinson.
We didn't, I said, you just joined us to that, you know, join us and never seen him.
And he came and he picked up, I think Sean was with us.
Yeah, he's though, I was with us.
And then he stopped us at a shoe store.
Yeah.
Oh, he just, these people were so good to us.
We just didn't know how to act.
I mean, that man had more video stations coming down the, the interview.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
And a lot of, and who interviewed us, I wish we could get that, who interviewed us the
most was his daughter, his daughter and her friends.
Then we would sit out on the patio and that man had more, uh, radio stations there.
Then we could, we can imagine.
We did a lot of interviews in Connecticut.
And pictures with, yeah, pictures with, yeah, that we can't, that we can't.
I asked Miss Robinson, she said, oh, no, they are United County.
They belong to the, they belong to the I-Pas of Jack and Robinson Foundation.
I said, well, can you be on a, going there and get a look up and said, no, I can't
actually.
She was such a sweetheart.
The daughter was to all, the whole family treated us very well.
Very nice.
Very well.
I mean, we learned things that I don't think we were able to learn.
She made sure we went to a museum.
Now she, yeah, she made sure, uh, me, I don't know what, sharing her, the daughter, she didn't
want to go to the museum, but Miss Robinson made, uh, take us to the museum and pass the
building.
And, and, and then she took us to the cell, placed with it.
She wanted us to see how they made sandals and all kind of stuff like that.
They just was just pure wonder for people, beautiful home.
Never seen a home like that in my life.
It was just, just pure gorgeous.
It was, everything was gorgeous, even though the lake, the lake was gorgeous.
And, and, and David, I have to put on tape, David, if you ever see this tape, you and
that horse got on my neck.
He rode a horse all the time.
Now, he would never bother joining too much, but he would aggravate me.
He would follow me and ask, I said, David, go somewhere, go.
And he would, how would they be one?
He was little.
He was like seven to eight, one.
Jack Robinson.
Yeah, he was little.
He was little.
He was little boy.
He was sick, man.
When, when we all came back from, from New York and settled back into, to say, Augustine,
we're now past the Civil Rights Act's passage in July 64.
And, all day, tell me about what happened here and did, the extent to which things did
and didn't change in the near term and how you felt about that.
Well, to me, everything stayed the same, but what I did was, I enrolled in a plot of
a moral thinking that, you know, the college was going to still be here.
You know, I said, well, you know, this is because we, we, we, we, we, uh, join.
Matter of fact, everybody went to college, but with a car.
Samuel went to Florida, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, my, join went to, it was all the
college.
And, uh, when, when this college moved, when they moved the college, I couldn't go with
the college because I didn't have the finance, the gold to my amy, you know, with the college.
So I had to drop out the college, you know, but Samuel, I think Samuel had about three,
three years of college.
Or maybe more, more, yeah, Samuel, Samuel was bringing.
Samuel was very smart, very, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I have to give it to him.
He was, he had a brain on him for him to, when I, the way he did, it, it, it, it really
broke my heart.
I, I think about him now because we had a lot of talks and, and Samuel was very, very
inspirational and, that was the brotherhood and all about the brotherhood and he loved
the brotherhood to talk about how, how the world needs to change and all, he was just,
yeah, he was very, very, very, not really called.
He died 95.
I didn't get a chance though because he was in Germany.
He died in Germany and his mother had his body shipped here from Germany.
I moved away.
He moved.
Yes, I moved to Jacksonville.
I went to school over there.
I met my husband.
I just stayed over there.
Yes, sir.
But, was part of that, were you, were there parts of not being here that were actually
helpful?
Yes, because I told my mother I was going to move to a city if I ever got married.
So I wanted my children to come up different from what I did.
I wanted them to have privileges if they wanted to learn how to swim.
They had pools or kind of pools.
They could just go, they couldn't tell them about it.
You can't come here because we didn't have a pool.
I think, what the college taught my mom I had a pool and the YMCA and we couldn't go
to YMCA because we were black.
So there was, no, no pools for us.
So that's why I told my mother, I just moved to the city for my children's sake.
So they could get a better education in the city.
That's where I did.
Well, okay.
We're going for a while.
We're going.
What, we're back after a short break.
Can you stand up to this over?
I think maybe after we turned off, we're just before after our break.
I wanted to ask you about other things that, important ways you think back on all this
history, when you, when you talk about it and think about it and other incidents, episodes,
themes, just invite you however you might want to comment.
Well, I just think about the things that we did and we know that we did what we thought
was right and we demonstrated in the way that we just didn't hurt nobody.
It was just a passive demonstration.
It was a non-violent movement and we just gave our all and all.
We did what we thought was right.
And I still say to this day, we was right and we didn't hurt nobody and go into jail if
we have to go again.
We did and we just did what we thought was right and I hurt.
That's what we wanted to do.
Make a difference.
It was time for a change.
If you don't do anything, you stay in the same old rut.
So we just had to get out and do what we thought was right and did.
It started a whole chain reaction.
Dr. Haling had to get somebody else in besides himself and from a more college and us
little 16 demonstrators he called in a big force.
So we just started the kindling of the fire, warning, yearning for what was due to us.
And we made a big dent and impact.
But we finished up with Dr. King and the passing of the Civil Rights Bill.
Do you think it changed the way you were thinking about what the path of your life might
be, what you wanted to do with your life?
Well really it changed the path of me thinking what it would be for my children.
That's what I wanted because my life had already I was 15 and I moved away after the
demonstrations and went to college.
So I wanted my children to have a chance better than what I had coming up.
So I moved to Jacksonville.
I liked it and I stayed there and read all my children.
I read full children there.
How about yourself and leadership role as a woman?
Did it change the way you thought about it?
No I'm very outspoken.
I'm just an outspoken person.
When I see something happening and it's not you know appropriately right or whatever,
I'm the first one divorced opinion of that's not right.
You can't do that.
You should do this or do that.
No that's just me.
I just forced my opinion on things now more because I always tell my kids when you write
you're right.
You can't say anything.
You just have to accept what they give you but always be right and try to do what's
right.
And then you can go ahead and voice your opinion.
I'm sorry but that's just something within me.
That's what I feel about.
Well, I think that's the other parts of the story that are really important to make
sure in the record.
Do you think that?
When I think back?
Well, when I think back on the what we went through, we went through a lot and we thought
we was going to accomplish a lot but to me, we accomplished a little.
Especially in synogue steam.
Synogue steam to me remains the same.
They give you a little and they snatch the back to me.
That's my opinion.
And for my life and the in the community, I feel like with the civil rights movement
and the part that we played in the civil rights movement made a difference to a certain
extent.
But it also made us lose a lot of our history and that's the hurting part of it all.
And I'm happy to see that our kids has a better chance of equal opportunity now than they
did before.
But to me, I see as I look back on my life back in the 60s and early 70s.
To me, it was a good life.
It was a good life.
The only thing we were second class citizens, that's what we wanted to change.
We wanted to change the let people know that we are humans.
We, our ancestors, were part of heaven, built this country.
And that is the reason we made this thing.
We were tired of being treated like a nobody.
And we had to be right as a white man.
You raised your family?
I raised my family.
My daughter moved to Jacksonville.
My son eventually moved to Jacksonville.
I have a son.
He stays in Kingsville.
So they grown.
But I raised him here.
My son, my baby boy, with the Synagosteen High.
And he was a quarterback for two years at the Synagosteen High School.
They almost were champions.
But they didn't get the political outcome.
But anyway, Synagosteen, to me, is the same old, same old.
It had to get rid of Ivory Doctor Helen.
And they had to get rid of the ones that voiced opinion and put their foot down and say,
oh no, I'm not taking this.
I'm not going to go for this.
Doctor Helen was not a yes man.
He was not a yes man.
Are there ways your record of activism had implications when you later in your life here
in the Synagosteen?
Yeah, to a certain extent.
But I made a good living for me and my kids.
I made a good living.
But I could have made a better living if I hadn't had that record over my head.
But sometimes God opened those for a reason.
And maybe that record, it may not mean anything right now.
But one day, maybe it will.
Because at least I have one.
They didn't destroy it.
And to be presented at my housewoman with the FBI file, that was the hardest thing I
can believe when David Nolan, the historian, stood up and said, I have a gift for you.
I have your FBI file.
And I'm like, what are you talking about?
FBI.
And he got Dr. Helen and they roll over.
I was like, what in the world is, did you mean to tell me we was monitored by the FBI
children?
You said as children.
14, 15, and 60.
You should see the pages of this.
I mean, he gave me this big old spec.
And I was so stunned.
I was like, are you?
Are you serious?
Or FBI file?
I had it when 2000.
2000, oh, when you had 2000 now, no, it was in 2008, when the housewoman.
That's all it does.
I never knew.
We never knew.
I never knew that.
You just found that out.
And he had the dedication of my house.
And that was a gift from him to me.
He said, Miss Audrey, I want to present you with your FBI file.
My mouth flew open and said, what are you talking about?
What FBI file?
And he had me this book.
And I opened it up.
And the first thing hit me in the face was Dr. Helen.
I was like, are I being hailed?
All kind of stuff in this FBI file.
I got it on.
I'm not sure the mics were caught.
I had a lot of questions about Dr. Helen's comment.
Could you just quickly repeat that?
Or should I?
That your home is a half-out for humanity home and it bears and it's front yard of plaque
talking about the history and your role in history.
And it's also a memorial I lived out by a cemetery.
And then the back of it is Samia Willikaw and Joran's mother.
And quite a few other civil rights activists that is buried in that.
So when they told me about the plaque, I said, well, I will prefer the plaque to be a
memorial for the ones that's buried in the back in the cemetery back there.
Special for Willikaw and Samia.
Now Joran's mother is buried inside him.
And Miss Hadith, why?
I'm a final question.
You've been up the road in Jacksonville for these years.
So very recently there was almost literally nothing in the local landscape of public history.
And this is a city after all that really presents its history as the drawing car for so many
tourist visitors.
There was almost nothing in the landscape that spoke to the civil rights era.
And quite recently, a monument now is in the plaza to the foot soldiers of the movement.
And I wonder if I wonder how you think about that placement and its significant standards.
Well, in 2004, before it's occurred, did there acknowledgement of the Synogostean for?
They acknowledged us as the fore youth who was sent away to the Reformatory School and
they invited people to come.
They had a big celebration.
And I'll form a lawyer, son came and he spoke.
Earl Johnson.
Earl Johnson, Jr.
Earl Johnson was our lawyer doing the demonstration and Mr. Dews.
So before we was acknowledged to everybody, and I worked for the state.
So nobody really knew what Joe Ann was all about until it was publicized in the newspaper.
But I used to go to my sister's school because she's a teacher and do black history.
But when it hit the newspapers and everywhere, they was like, oh my god, Joe Ann, I don't
have to go around with a sign on me saying how I feel.
That was in my heart, not in believe I had to share that with nobody.
But after I shared it with everyone, they shared it and acknowledged us and we just came
until some.
I was doing that with Joe Ann, but you do this.
So I think it made a big impact on our life later after they had acknowledged.
But we felt like, I'm going to tell you the way I felt.
I don't know about it.
You never felt that way.
We felt like what we did didn't really make a difference to nobody because nobody gave
us no good feedback.
It's up or something of the role.
They just kept us like, who?
We all went from church.
They had things and they did it for themselves.
They didn't acknowledge us for nothing.
And that made me feel bad.
I told all of you there to be all right.
It'll be all right and do time.
But I really think what we did was just the right thing to do.
And I don't care.
You know, it's all right whether they acknowledge us or not.
God knows our heart.
And we did a whole lot to make life better for everybody.
That includes for our family, your family, anybody that's prejudiced.
Let them know the way we feel.
We deserve everything that we get because we are human too.
Just because we're different color doesn't mean I don't deserve that.
You deserve different.
No.
The first amendment.
We all deserve the same thing.
And that's the way I feel.
I just felt like what we did was right now.
I'm just sorry if I hit on people are hatred and they feel bad and they just figure
they're just animosity.
They just got all that hatred in their heart.
If you're not of your color, then I'm wrong.
But that doesn't, that's not the way it goes.
There's a lot of people live that way and they think and I probably work with them.
Some of them side by side.
But you kept your thoughts over there to yourself and after Joanne left the room.
I always say you probably say Joanne's a good old, you know what?
But it's alright because Joanne is three days better than I.
I ain't got time for it.
You know, it's just...
But I'm gonna say this.
I'm gonna say this.
The Fourth of a Corps was the first to put anything downtown concerning the civil right
movement.
And what happened to us as teenagers before the footstones, the footstones, the footstones
the monuments down there, the Fourth of a Corps had already acknowledged us downtown on
the wall next to the Woodward.
Donald and Duncan, I have to give her props for getting all these monuments out the way
that she has did.
Because if it wasn't for her and her belief in talking with Mr. City Commissioner, former
City Commissioner, Twine and Mrs. Katherine Twine, they gave her a vision.
She called me and I told her, I said, Grunland, if you want to know anything or need to know
anything, you need to get in touch with Dr. Helen.
You need to go in and talk to Dr. Helen because Dr. Helen, because during that time they
were having our anniversary here.
I said, you talk to Dr. Helen, he'll put you on the right track for whatever need to be
dead in Santa Augustine because they swept the whole movement up under the rug.
Not just the Santa Augustine fall, but the whole movement of Santa, if they could have
got rid of everything, they pushed down the ponds out there on US one, they got rid of
that.
They pushed down the monsoon, they got rid of that.
Not a change to slave market.
Anything that they could get rid of, concerning the civil right movement, they got rid of until
seven people in this town like Barbara Vickers, Dr. Arby Helen, Wolland Duncan and her
members said, no, we are not having it.
We are not having it.
Somebody go know what happened in Santa Augustine.
Somebody go know because we're going to make sure.
Thank you.
This has been a presentation of the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum
of African American History and Culture.