From the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.
Mrs. Warren.
Okay.
We're all in.
Today is Tuesday the 13th of September 2011.
My name is Joe Manier of the Southern oral history program at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
I'm with videographer John Bishop in St. Augustine, Florida, specifically at the Bayfront Health Inn,
where we are recording several oral history interviews for the Civil Rights History Project,
which is a joint undertaking of the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and the Library of Congress.
We also have with us today here in the room where we're recording Dr. Robert Hailing, who will also be a series interviewee.
And we're especially pleased to have the chance to be with you today.
Mrs. Vickers, Mrs. Barbara Henry Vickers.
And we are here to talk about the movement history of St. Augustine.
And we will bring that story all the way up through the current year, because of course we'll talk about the monument.
So let me just say thank you, and we appreciate you're sitting down.
And that was a pleasure.
I know, Mrs. Vickers, that you came up in St. Augustine. Could you talk to a little bit about your family and your childhood in the city?
Yes, I was raised in St. Augustine, and I went to a parochial school, Catholic school, St. Benedict,
which wasn't too far from my home.
And I finished that school in eighth grade, and I went to Excelsior High School, which was the only black school, high school for blacks.
And I graduated from Excelsior.
And you would have graduated about nineteen.
And you would have graduated from high school, yes, nineteen forty two, thirty eight, thirty nine from the Royal School.
Forgive me one quick interruption, I forgot to mention that we are not recording to the HD cards.
That's correct. That's correct. Excuse me for that interruptions.
Can you tell me a little about your parents, and did you have siblings?
Well, my mother and father both did hotel work.
And in fact, my mother worked as a waitress here at this hotel, and it went back, and it was the Montsehnt Hotel at that time.
And she was to ride her bike.
Back most people in St. Augustine were to ride her bike here, and my father worked a few doors down.
It was the Bennett Hotel, and he was a matrede, which they called the head waiter at that particular time.
And he worked at that, but he had a little car they called Rippy, and he drove the car.
He was the only one in the family that had the car.
Rest of the ladies had to ride their bikes, even if it was raining, they had to ride their bikes, but that would just go his merry way.
They didn't pick them up, but that's how they got back and forth.
And at this particular hotel, they served three meals a day, breakfast lunch in dinner.
And in the morning, I can remember mother having the black, I think it was the black uniforms.
They wore the head black for morning, I think, and white in the evenings, and they all had their little A-forms and their little piece on top of the head.
And I had my mother working here, my grandmother and my aunt, all three of them.
I happened to have found my picture there the other day with my aunt on it, but I didn't find my mother.
Did you have brothers and sisters?
I have, once I was living, I lost my sister that was underneath about a year and a half ago, maybe two years.
I was the oldest sister, and when I was born, I was nine years old, so I'm nine years older than Grandola.
And Charlotte, the baby sister, I'm 19 years older than that sister.
So the two of us, we talk every day, and we have a good relationship.
Are there important parts of how you thought about the city related to race and race relations that you'd like to share in the years before we reached the 60s?
Well, when I finished school, I couldn't finish fast enough, and I couldn't get away from sin-orvesting fast enough.
With the intention of never, never coming back again, only to visit my parents.
Tell me what motivated that feeling of sin.
Sin-orvesting was a racist, racist sound.
And I was just tired of you go to the grocery store, and if white people came in, then you'd have to get in the back of the line and wait till you turn.
And sometimes it would take quite a while to get out of the store.
And several times I'd have to get off the sidewalk, because white people would not move, and they would kind of spread out, so you would have to get off the sidewalk.
And I just thought that if life was better anywhere, I would try to find a better life.
And it happened that way, but I ended up coming back, you know, later years after, under stood life a little better, things weren't quite as bad.
When did you move away?
Right after high school, and last to 42.
I moved to New York, and I stayed there about, or I was in about four years.
And they had an urge of working in the shipyard doing the war, and they needed people to well.
So I went there, and they sent you to school, and I learned how to tack well.
And I got this job on the ship, and I was doing the tack well then.
And it was nerve-wracking to me being from the south. They were all white men on the ship.
And I guess it was my imagination, but they looked like they were the meanest people in the world when you would get on.
And I would come with my little southern ball, good morning, and nobody answered they were all too busy doing what they had to do.
So I would sit there, because if they could not fit apart, you know, with the blueprints, then I would have nothing to do but just sit.
And when they could fit apart, then they would call tack, and then I would go and put it together.
But eventually, I warmed down, and eventually I had them all laughing on the ship, and they would say, good morning to me before I could get on the ship.
Because I never stopped saying good morning, because I just raised that way, and you just say good morning is the human thing to do.
And when I left, I left to go to Seattle, and I thought I was going to be well than there at Boeing's Aircraft, and they were upset that I was leaving.
And we had that relationship, and when I got to Seattle, I found out that they weren't using me as a welder, they're using me as a mechanic helpful.
And I didn't quite like that as well. I just liked the welding, but I stayed and accepted, and I worked on the graveyard ships, the night ship, because I don't like to get up early in the mornings.
So I enjoyed that. And I stayed there for quite a while, and one night, it's girlfriend of mine, Corine was my friend, and I would have her going from job to job, because I didn't like the job.
And until she got tired, and she said, oh, you leave, I'm not leaving, I like this job. But when she said she would go to the shipyard, and she enjoyed it.
And then I said, let's go to Seattle, before she said, why you get less money going to Seattle, and we have a good job here.
But I wanted to travel, see what Seattle was all about, and move around. I was 19, I think, at that time. And she said she'd go.
But I got to the train station, and no Corine. And I said there, and I said, and I was almost in tears, and I said no, because she's coming. I know she'll be here.
And I knew one of the photos there from St. Augustine, and he took my bags on early. And he said, it's time to go, and no Corine.
So I got on the train, and then I felt the train moving, then the tears did come. But later on, there was a telegram thing, Barbara Henry.
And she asked me to wait for her in Chicago, and she had missed the train. I was never so happy all the days of my life.
Going out there didn't know anybody, but I figured the two of us would be together. So anyway, when she got to Chicago, I got off, and I took the L to ride the L,
because I'd never been on the L before, you know, I wanted to see what that was all about. And I came back, and we went on to Seattle.
When did you come back to St. Augustine?
I came back to St. Augustine after I married 80 Bickers. He was from St. Augustine, and we had been dating off and on.
And he had no intentions, no desire to do anything, because he was just in love with St. Augustine.
So I would go to Jersey every year, and it was a bellhawk. So this particular summer, he came over and decided that we would get married.
I didn't discuss where we were going to live, but that night after we married, he says, well, are we going to St. Augustine?
And of all the names in the world, St. Augustine? I said, we're not going to St. Augustine. He says, oh yes, we are.
So the marriage kind of sold a little bit, because I said I'm not going. So he gave me a week. He said he was leaving, he'd come back to St. Augustine, and he gave me a week to come back.
So it was a hard decision to meet, and I had gotten a nice job and everything. And I came back, and after that, things broke out and St. Augustine with the civil rights.
Do you remember what year it was when it was that you arrived back here?
I guess I came back in the late 50s, because it was about the 60s when I think Dr. Heeland had everything going.
How did you first become acquainted with Dr. Heeland?
But Dr. Heeland was a neighbor. He stayed across the street. And I'd seen him coming and going, and I would go to the meetings, the rallies and the meetings and whatnot.
And he was asking for people to go to the different places for the cities and the Nielins and all these different things.
He hadn't said too much, but that night that Dr. King came, Dr. Heeland told him that he needed people to go to the churches.
I don't know whether it was planned or not, but Dr. King looked at me in the church of all people. And he said, young lady, will you go?
And I said, yes, and I thought to myself, what did I say?
Just by chance, he called you out.
So that's what started me going to the Nielins. And then the first Nielin, and I went to the wooden letters in the church.
So the two young men, young white fellows, said we'd have to go back to the office to report to Dr. Heeland.
And that was a mistake. He says, go to another church. I'm thinking it's time to go home. I've done my duty. It's time to go home.
And he said, well, my dear, that's his word. You just go to this church and that church. So that's how I got involved.
And I didn't miss the meetings or anything. All of the meetings and what was going on.
And we were, we called out to the Scotts Street, 11. It was on Scotts Street. And it's 11 houses on Scotts Street.
Every home had a particular job. It was, it wasn't the city, it was the Nielins, the sleeping, swimming. They all had their particular job.
So Julia Conway, of course, the street from the Purcell Conway's mother. She decided that we were going to be a group.
And we had to protect Dr. Heeland. I don't know how we were going to protect him.
But the West Side Boys came and they were in the trees and all around Dr. Heeland House to protect him.
Because I don't know. I don't think he had any nerves. Because he was out there in the street and knew the people were behind him.
And I would just be so nervous. I said, well, why don't he get in that house and be quiet until the next day.
But he was always active. So those boys were there. And we formed this little network that when the clans came through House Street, we would call each other and let each other know.
And most of the time we would, they said, you better get down because they're shooting low.
And a lot of times we would cook from refrigerator to open the refrigerator door.
And it was just real scary. And Dr. Heeland would be out there and I would be peeping. And they would be peeping to make sure that he get in the house okay.
But he was nervous. Because I remember one night my aunt was sick and my call wouldn't start.
And I called his office and asked him if I could get a ride home. And he says, well, it'll be late, my dear. So it was late.
I guess it's maybe like 3 o'clock in the morning. He called and he came to pick me up. And do you know? He did not go home.
He went downtown in a red boat you had him at the top going back. There I am sitting up there riding with him downtown. No cause on the street though.
And I said, Dr. Heeland, where are you going? And he says, I have to make my night deposit my dear.
My son night deposit knew me not being here the next morning. And I said, well, from that day to this, I had not had another ride with Dr. Heeland.
That was enough for me that night. But he just would do what he had to do. And the night that they shot, we would collect food.
And the different ones with like a five fix something tonight, maybe two of us would fix something to make a meal for the boys that were protecting him.
And this particular night, I understand most of them went to sleep. And they shot into Dr. Heeland's home. And I knew you heard that story about the kid.
When I came home, there was an officer in the middle of Scott Street. And he said, you can't go in. It's been a shooting.
So I said, well, I live on Scott Street. So he said, okay, we'll go on in. So Julia came across the street. And she said, he was a huge cop.
And she says, I gave Fatso a chair so he could sit down because he looked like he was out of his. And I said, well, I wouldn't have given him anything.
He probably one of the ones that's been shooting through here. But anyway, they shot Dr. Stolz, Madonna, and the boxer.
And he was crazy about that dog because at night, when he would come home, he would walk Madonna out there walking Madonna.
But after that, he had friends. And I guess he thought the Aster's with the keep his children. And until he could take them down to Tallahassee.
But people, I don't know. I don't know whether they were afraid or what. But the next-door neighbor, she said, bring the girls over and I'll keep them.
And his wife was pregnant. She was pregnant from the third child. And she had just gotten off the sofa with a bullets.
And then it refused to, I mean, we were all in danger. So you might as well just take the child. I mean, you weren't saved. Nobody was saved.
And he did get the kids. And I guess he took them to Tallahassee because you never know what he was going to do.
And one day, I remember he said that they were going to Tallahassee to talk to the governor.
And I said, but why are you asking me to go? I don't need to go. Whatever he said, yeah, we need different people from different churches. And I was Catholic.
So we went. And that was another scary ride because I was looking back. I just knew cause was betraying us and was going to shoot because we had those incidents going to Butler's Beach.
You know, they would run you off the road and just to intimidate you. And we went and we talked to the governor there and whatnot.
And they didn't do much good then until you know, later on in Dr. Haley, we didn't talk to Dr. King about coming.
But how did you, first let me ask just this quickly, what were you and your husband doing for work then?
For work in New York or San Augustine? When you came back here, I was a beautician.
And I had my own salon at home where we fixed that and you could do, you could be given papers to allow to have it at home.
And he worked at that particular time for driving movie theater. And he was a gambler.
And I'll say very good gambler because he always had the money when it was time. And I don't know, I just didn't like the idea that he didn't have any particular real job even though he was paying the bill.
So I confronted him about that. And he said, why should I worry about that as long as I've been taking care of.
But Coach Calhoun, Solomon Calhoun, they have a building in San Augustine, not that they named after him. He was my basketball coach during the time I was in high school.
And he had gotten him this job at the Recreation Center. So that's how he got to be a recreation director and had the little links and all of the kids.
He was a father figure to kids. And he would put kids before anybody. Me too.
And I would say, well, Vickers, what he said, well, I had the voice that little boy shoes. I said, why? He said because he wouldn't have shoes that play softball or whatever.
But he looked out for them and the mothers would come to him and ask him where are the kids. And he said, just go home. I'll get him home.
And he seemed to know where the kids would hang out or where they would be. He would be father and scold them.
Okay, Coach, I won't do it again.
Yeah. So I want to come back to that. I'm sorry. I kind of knocked you off the trajectory of the events on Scotts Street.
But I asked about your employment partly to get a sense of how you managed through such a period of stress and tension during that period of all that violence and perspective violence and the fear of violence, how you managed through that.
I don't know because in the shop at one time I had blankets up so you couldn't see the light from the outside. And most of the customers were afraid to come because they didn't want to come and be caught out there.
And then something happened to them, the same with Doc in his office. You know, his customers were afraid to go to the office and whatnot.
But it didn't bother me too much because Vickers was a very good provider. And he took care of me. And I really didn't have that to worry about.
So if I didn't have any customers, I didn't need them.
And I just enjoyed my work anyway because I never got really paid for what I did because if I knew a family that couldn't afford it and they had four or five kids for Easter,
I wouldn't charge the mother. And people say, oh, I know you loaded with the traffic that you had sometimes wouldn't have too much.
And then the mothers would come at their sad stores and they would bring back. And then I had some con people that would try to get over and tell you, I left my money home, I'll bring it back.
And you never see that until it's time to make another appointment. But I enjoyed my work. I couldn't have done it if I didn't have Vickers to take care of me.
Did the clan of a march openly down the Scotts Street? Did they open the clan march as a group?
No, no. They marched over in Lincoln's Hill. But not on the Scotts Street. They came through their like bullies, you know, just shooting and showing their authority and just intimidating.
Because I remember one night I was coming from one of the rallies and they were throwing rocks from upstairs.
And the cop had stopped me and he pulled over and he asked me, did I have any weapons? So I said no. So he said, open the trunk. I opened the trunk.
And he got the wrench that you changed the tire red. And he said, you do have a weapon. So I said, well, that's the tire red. And he said, there's still a weapon and I could arrest you.
And it just, I mean, it just made you nervous. I mean, and he could. I mean, what could you do about it? If he said you're on the rescue, just on the red.
And even with that, I still went back and forth every night and I had this little car that would break down on every corner and have to get other people to remember.
But it, it, I had a drive that I had to be there. And I wanted to know what was going to happen next and what was going to be done.
All of the people could tell you, but you know how I'd go when I have to two or three people tell you something is not the same.
And Julia, my girlfriend, Crosha, she was good at that. She didn't want to win. It wouldn't even be that way. So I just, I just had to, had to be there. It was a drive.
Because I felt like after, Dr. Haley went and asked Dr. King, he turned him down the first time he wouldn't come. But when he finally got him here, and that night he asked me about would I participate in the churches?
I thought to myself, if there's going to be a change, this is the time. And they need people. So you can't just sit there and wait for it to happen. You have to be a part.
So that's why I did it. I mean, I just, and my sister, she said she was afraid she didn't go. Neither one of them, one of them, when was in Baton, Brooklyn, college, and Daytona. And she didn't go.
Because my grandmother, if she could keep it from going, she would do that. And she would sit on TV and she said, why are they doing that?
She said, those white people will never let them eat with them. I said, we don't want to eat with them. We want to be free. We want to be able to go to the restaurant, pay our money and have the food, not taking it out the back door.
She said, but we've been doing that all these years. I said, but it's time out for that. She says, where are you going to kill me? I said, Mama, you just have to die.
So, so they didn't bother me. And after she did the same thing, she said, you keep going out in. I don't know whether you're going to come back safely.
I'll be dead when you come back. I said, and I don't say that you're sick. And you know, I'm going to see you're going to die anyway. You sit. I mean, she was terminally ill. And I said, I'm going.
And I just, I don't know. I just felt like the time was right.
You have children at the time?
I have a son that I inherited from one of them. And he was five years old and he's certified now.
He is the best thing that ever happened to me. But you did not have children at that time.
No.
You weren't also looking over your children and the midst of all this.
How did you recall that? What are the memories that come most vividly to mind when you think about some of the protests, some of the church visits, some of the, all that happened here?
Some of the people, I think they wanted to do things. But they have their peers and their garden clothes and listen to it.
They couldn't afford to be apart or let them know even if they would do little things for black people behind their backs or something like that.
And then there was something. There was just a few devils. They were just evil people.
And I don't know. And I just, well, I never wanted to do housework anywhere. I'm not a housekeeper now. I never will be too late now.
But to work for them and to see how they were talked to people. And you have to go to the back door to get the paper from the front.
If the paper is on the front porch, you still have to go around the back, come in the house to go to the front post to pick the paper up.
And you just pick the paper up and go, I don't know. And that bothered me. I just didn't want to live that kind of life.
And I thought, you know, getting away from here, like going to New York. And I did factory work when I first went there.
I was always doing things with my hand and did factory work. And that kept me from working in homes and whatnot.
And let me ask you about this. And you might be, you might look, okay, we're going to take a quick break.
Okay. Let me take another shot. We'll see if there's more to bring in. Is that okay?
Yeah. I want to ask, I think you might be able to share some perspective that we probably can't get otherwise in our visit to San Augustina.
I wonder if you could be in the neighbor right across the street. I wonder if you could talk a little bit about Mrs. Haling and how you observed her bear up through all this.
Mrs. Haling was a very quiet person. She didn't make ways. And you didn't see that much of her. Only when she had the two little girls and she brought them over across the street to get the hair done or something like that.
But most of the time she was in the house. I don't know if that was because of the danger of being outside or she was just that type of person.
But you couldn't meet a sweet of person. She was just lowkey. Very sweet.
Did she, that's a tremendous, obviously, tremendous level of stress for a family to face. That kind of threat of violence.
That threat of violence. Men obviously are coming to help protect the house and all.
Do any other kind of thoughts or recollections about all of that, all of the family had to face in those ways.
Don't you Haling being attacked and beaten all those sorts of things?
No, I didn't see it in her. Because I didn't see it that much. But I know it had to. Because he worried me.
And I'm cautious of street from. And just the neighbor. So you can imagine what a wife would feel.
Not knowing whether he's going to even come home or not. And then when he gets home, then he goes down the street. But the box of dogs.
So she had, it had to upset her. I know I went to Fort Lauderdale one time it was during the Christmas.
And Grin said, that's Miss Haling. So we wanted to speak to her. By the time we get close to her, she'd cross the street.
And Grin would turn around and come around and we get close to her. She'd cross the street.
So I said, Miss Haling, Miss Haling, this is Barbara from St. Augustine. And she stopped and she said that her brother, I think it's her brother, had just been robbed at the fillings station.
Because in the summer, I had just been robbed at the fillings station and she was trying to get the dogs back home. I guess you didn't want to go through no more drama or whatnot.
Did you have any further interaction with Dr. King or with?
No, the first time that Dr. King came, they said Dr. King was coming in. Dr. Haling and I had set up with the different businesses to meet him.
And I was president of the beautician association. But I didn't have time for Dr. King. There was a convention going on in Daytona.
So I had to go to the convention and I asked Queenie Mitchell McCall now if she would go in my state and represent the beauticians.
And she said, well, you're not going to stay in Dr. King? Well, he wasn't really famous then, you know, like Dr. Dr. Kagan now, you know.
And he was doing wonderful things. But to me, it was more important for me to go to this beautician thing.
So then when he got famous and everything, I said, oh, I missed the boat. I'll never have that chance again. But he did come back.
And then that night that I did meet him, he was supposed to be the same Paul church they told me.
And I was late because one of my customers made me late. And they said, no room in St. Paul, you have to go to first Baptist.
I said, no, I want to go with Dr. King. They said he would be both places. So I went to first Baptist and Reverend Avenue was there.
And then Dr. King came over after that. And that's when I met him. And then we all had chance to shake his hand and everything after everything was over.
And his hands were just like cotton. It's a soft thing. And then he never forgot a name.
They said that once he got your name, if he saw you a year from now, he could call you by name.
But that was quite an experience. Yeah.
How did you respond to being turned away at the Nielins?
Well, I expected it. And no one said, I know. But I went to the Grace Methodist Church. And there was an insurance man that came every Monday. And that was his living.
And he came in. I said, now he comes to my door every Monday to get my money. And his feet looked like it was that long.
I know they were at that long. But when he put his feet right down, I was kneeling. And he put his feet like that. It just looked like it was big foot.
And I just knew I said, oh, if he kicked me down the steps, I was in harm. And I said, because I know what he's thinking, the nerve of her thinking that she can come in here and worship with us.
And that Monday, this was that Sunday, that Monday, he was to my door. And I said, I don't believe you are to my door. And he says, well, what?
I said, and you who are there to your church, because you're not supposed to talk to white people like that. But I said, if you don't get away from him, don't you ever come back here again.
It was Metropolitan Life Insurance, right back there. And I didn't think about canceling the insurance, returning it in the thing. I just dropped it.
Didn't worry about it anymore. Just upset me so. But other than that, at the other places, it was just something expected.
Like, my niece was saying she saw this movie, the hell. And she said, but people live like that. It was about the maids and how they talk to the maids. I said, well, that happened.
But she said, well, how did you do that? I don't think I could take that. I said, it was a real life.
I said, if you had to stand in line and you had babies to feed, you had to get baby food. You just move out the line and move on in when you could get the baby food.
I said, that's why you all say I'm a fanatic about the civil rights, but I just felt good to know that we were going to have a chance.
And you know, other people wouldn't have to go through all that. The kids are today. And like I say, with the voting rights and what people went through, and I asked the kids now that can vote that they vote.
I just, well, I just can't believe it. Like my sister told me with the monument. I said, I can't believe the people are not donating and participating, trying to help get the monument there.
She said, because they don't feel the way you do about the monument. The monument, it just meant the world to me because it recognized all of those people that came here, that you had nothing about.
Dr. Haley, Dr. Young, Dr. King, yes. But they couldn't have done it alone. They needed everybody who participated. And they put their lives on the line. They could have been killed.
Some of those college students left college. The parents paying for them to go to college. It might have been the last money they had to send them to college. And they didn't say it all, it's been fighting for civil rights. And they were white. They didn't have to do that.
And I thought, what other way could you do to recognize those people?
What did you think of the idea of first come to you and when?
I guess about 10 years ago. And other people were talking about the monuments. And I had gone with these different groups. And I didn't mention the foot soldiers. I just said a monument.
But they were thinking about a king monument or whatever. And then when they said, I went ahead and I did this with the monument and thinking they were trying to do, they were not trying to do foot soldiers monument. They were not.
They were trying to do a monument. And nothing is preventing them for putting up the kind of monument that they wanted. I didn't want that.
I talked to Dr. Hailey. Guess what he said.
Well, my dear. Can't you just get a plaque on Marker? I said no. I want a monument. Do you know what the head and tails? Yes. Hard work. But we're going to get a monument.
He said, and then he would call my dear. I wish you would just settle. You could just put a plaque on the ground. Dr. Hailey. We are going to have a monument.
How did you begin to organize towards that? It happened. Council on Asian. The. Kathy Brown. The way. Kathy Brown was the director. And she wanted to organize.
And Mayor Senior Advisory Committee to help the city and know what they wanted to do. So she organized it. And the president, something happened and he quit.
So then they say, well, maybe this won't work. I said, yes, it will. If you want it to work. So then they made me president.
I shouldn't have done that because I wasn't going to get well. And the president and I made it work. And I went one day and the secretary said, well, it's no meeting today because nobody signed up.
So I said, well, when did you have people assigned up? I mean, it's free to everybody to come and do. I said, don't do it that way. But what happened was the mayor was about to switch and think.
And they said, well, how do you know we're going to have the same mayor? I said, we don't. But we do it until we have another mayor. So we did this. And I went to Kathy one day. It just kept. I just kept thinking and thinking about the foot soldiers.
And I told her what my dream was. She says, that's good. She said, but if you do a Martin Luther King monument, you have better participation because immunity will rally and you get it done in no time.
I said, but that's not what I want. She said, what you want? I said, the foot soldiers, monument, the people who really put their lives on the line and whatnot. So she says, well, I don't know whether you can get money like that. I said, but I can try.
If you think so, she said, well, you ask God, the judge, God, it was a mayor. If not, then you can organize your own group. So he said he wasn't getting enough participation. So he says, we can switch over. So then we came up with the name, you know, the same foot soldiers. And then we went in to get the 5013C.
And we got it done. And one day, the Slating Nina Verilam, she called and she says, Barbara, I understand you trying to do this monument. She said, what does it take to get it started?
So I said to myself, now, if she's going to give a donation, just give it. What does it take to get started? She's not going to give that. And I said, well, we have a sculpture. And it's going to take at least 20,000 for him to get started. She says, you got it.
I was, she said, she said she thought I had fallen out. She said, because I didn't say anything for two, three minutes. I said, but I was so shocked. And then after then, you know, different ones would send in money and then money like that. And then my grandson says, he works for UPS. And he says, no, I'm going to try to get a grant from UPS.
And so he did. And we were emailing back and forth. I was doing all the wrong things. And they were trying to get it on my volunteer hours. And at that particular time, I had volunteer hours, because I'd volunteer anywhere was the volunteer.
And he said, yeah, he think they could get it. And they were just going to give us five thousand. But when the deal went down, they gave seven thousand and 400, I think it was. And I said, now I know it's no stopping now. And Dr. Hillen, they will not be a flat.
And what is kept coming in? What was your overall project budget?
Approximately. What did we have? What do you think you had to get all together around? Well, at first, we thought it was about 60,000, but altogether, around about 70,000 dollars.
How did you get from 27,000 and change all the way there?
Okay, we had the sculpture come to sign the contract. And we had that in the plaza. And he signed and then we gave him the 20,000 dollars to begin.
So this man walks up to me, he filled Mac Daniels. And he said, Barbara, he said, you're almost there. I said, no, we need another, at least another 20,000 dollars.
He said, okay, he says, I'll check within a couple of days. He said, we'll get that in one night. One night.
So he called and asked me to meet him to the lawyers, lawyer, Kahnan, Patrick Kahnan. And he was excited. I told him about the civil rights story and why I was interested in getting the foot soldiers and what it meant. And this that now, then he was all gone whole.
So he had his secretary to pull out a list, get on the phone and invite them for $100 a head. And he said, all I want you to do is get some of the people who took part in the civil rights movement to be there that night and talk to the people and get me a little bit of music.
And that I did. I got Del Kahn to play and Freddie Thompson, Freddie Thompson was one of the ones that was under the hedges with me when they beat Andy Young that night. And we were down up under the hedges that night in the rocks kept coming.
So he had a good story to tell. And any way that night, Phil raised 24,000. And look like the money was just, it's just coming. And I was so upset. And I kept telling my sister she said, I don't understand why you upset. This is your obsession. She says, you can't expect other people to feel the way you feel.
I felt like every church, every black church in St. Augustine would have been there to help. And they weren't. We got one black church, the poor church in St. Augustine that has very few members. They sent $100. Not another black church.
I don't know. Then the American Legion, I had been behind them. And they didn't do anything. But when Phil invited them, then they came through with their money.
Let me ask you about. I'm sorry. Okay. We're back after short break. I want to ask the, this is a complicated question or a straightforward question with a complicated answer. So I hope you'll take some time and help fill in all the complexity of it.
St. Augustine had done very, very little over the years to document in a public way. It's civil rights experience. In fact, many people would say that they did everything they could to kind of erase that history in a public sense. And here you wanted to bring a very prominent civil rights monument onto the very central plaza that has architecturally kind of defined the city, the heart of the city over its long, long history.
How did you navigate through that and what kind of reaction did you receive? Well, what happened? We went to the City Commission meeting with a proposal. There were two other groups that had gone there and asked permission to do a monument. They didn't say puts those in the monument. They wanted to do a monument. And the two groups were feuding. And the City Commission said for them to get together, come back.
And then they would, you know, see what they could do about it. So I was in one of the groups. So I left that group and I went to other group and tried to organize something to do the monument. And they said that it was their idea. And they had to do this. And we had to go on there and borrow and we're what not.
And so the people that I had with me that they have money and they were ready to, you know, put out money. They said, I don't think this is going to work. So then I said, well, and that's when I went on with Kathy and did they all love it?
Jack, I say they still have their chance to do what they want to do.
Oh, sure, sure. I was your sense of the city government's reaction to the whole process now completed.
The city was very slow. And they didn't help because I thought maybe that they were going to participate and think.
And City Commissioner, Earl Jones, he said that he had $5,000 a lot of them to do work downtown.
And let me say for the tape, excuse me, he's African American.
And that he would give us that. But then it rolled down to the city would use it, you know, not just give it. So they did the prep work and whatever for the money and thing.
And that was at the last minute after everything was done. And they did it that way. And then they follow in month.
They did the walkway for and the young with the footsteps and they paid for that.
The city paid for that.
The city paid for that. Yeah. So it's a lot.
And you know, I still don't understand, you know, but I can say that when I was having problems, I got good rapport from both the mayor and the city manager and the lawyer because they it was some lost things about the law and whatnot.
And I can't say anything against that. But send all the seniors a hole.
It still has a long way to go.
Yeah, put out for that. That way.
The money. Did any much of it on the income from the white business community?
The money that we raised practically all of it. We got very little from the black community.
Yeah. Now we got small donations, you know, from individuals and whatnot.
But most of all major donations that they now hanged Thomas that was with the freedom fighter.
He gave a sizable donation.
But say Phil McDaniels is white.
Yes. And McCann.
McCann's white. And then the lawyers that they gathered together then were the white attorneys mostly.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I was about to ask one thing. It's just slip my mind.
Oh, I know. I have to ask and I'm very interested in how did it feel on the day that you did the formal installation?
I think I just lost it.
I mean, it just is happening.
And my family came. I had my family from Fort Lauderdale.
I had 12 all together. They said I didn't seem nervous.
But I was nervous. And then it all happened.
And everybody spoke. And they called me to speak.
I just was lost to words. And I just, I was tired. I was tired.
Because when my family came, it takes a lot of, and I was already tired from going through with these others.
And I just was low-key. I didn't even talk to the doc that night much.
You know, the people were there. I just said, I was just lady.
I don't know the program when it was time for her to speak at the unveil of me.
Dr. Hailing is just she gave her hand wave.
And everybody laughed.
I don't think the microphone can probably pick that up.
So Dr. Hailing was just observing that at the ceremony when when when Miss Pickers was called to speak,
she just sort of waved her hand and like crowd rather than she just moved in.
And the crowd responded to the applause.
Yeah.
She had left out.
She has tremendous organization.
She doesn't take no from me.
And she will get on her telephone and work through her.
Yeah.
Agency on agent.
Yeah. Council.
You know.
Dr. Hailing, may I ask you about this tomorrow when we do a session just because I know the microphone is just not going to get you over there.
And it doesn't really do justice when I'm doing.
I feel a little bad when I have to repeat because I'm not doing justice.
But Dr. Hailing is making the point really crediting Miss Pickers with excellent organizational skills and real commitment and real determination to see it through.
Yeah.
To get to that to get to the result.
Sure.
I think I can think of short break.
We'll take a short break.
I don't know.
We'll roll in.
Okay. We're back on after break.
This is because I want to invite you to share any final thoughts.
But one last question from me before we before we do that.
My own personal sense of the monument significance is that of an outsider.
So I haven't spent any time in St. Augustine in my life.
And coming here and thinking about this history since it's kind of the work that I do.
It seems to me a quite significant thing that you've done to.
To give that all of this history of physical presence through a piece of art like that.
That will be here now and help define the city now.
And I wonder if it feels to you that maybe there will be some.
This might have long and important implications for the city over the years to come.
You might hope.
I hope.
Yeah.
Any any any final things that you might want to offer.
We've obviously just moved fairly quickly, quickly through a lot of history and a story of theme and issue.
Anything final perspective that you would like to share?
Doing this monument.
It took years.
And I met people that was working on the committee.
And it changed my perspective a little with white people.
I know they're all the not the same.
You know that.
And knowing what you've been through, you have some kind of bitter taste and you figure well.
Later on they're going to change you.
Going to find out their true colors.
And some are dead.
But it has brought closeness to some of the people that took part in the organization.
Doing the civil rights movement.
Meeting Dr. Hailing.
And all these years, you know, and we're still friends.
It means a lot.
That you know these people.
And I don't know like his brother now.
He never gives up.
And I thought maybe after leaving Sin Augustine, that that would be it for him.
That he will have had enough.
But I think.
Go with him to rest of his life.
And he feels the same thing where I do.
That it's still not enough done.
It's still so much to do.
I can't do it all.
He can't do it all.
But we can still try and try to keep things going.
Keep the young people motivated the ones you can.
It's some kids that you'll never reach.
But they are some.
And if you don't help but one or two.
And make them see the significance.
And our full fathers, what they went through with.
And I was reading something one day about downtown in the plaza.
Black people were caught after dark in the plaza.
They would be them.
I mean, that's just ridiculous.
But people lived through that.
And my grandmother used to tell me stories about, you know, how people would come in your homes and pull you.
Siddling's out, taking a mutton, hanging them and all that.
And I can't blame her for feeling the way she did.
I mean, those people lived through that.
I just heard it.
And I'm thinking I lived through something now.
No.
But if I can help to make a difference.
I'm still ready.
88.
Ready to go.
So real honor and privilege to be with you.
Thank you so much for sharing this interview with us.
Thank you.
This has been a presentation of the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.