From the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.
Today is Wednesday, July 13, 2011. My name is Joe Manier of the Southern Laurel History Program at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
I'm in Washington, D.C. in the Jefferson Building of the Library of Congress, which is the Art of For John Bishop.
And we are here to complete an oral history interview for the Civil Rights History Project, which is a joint undertaking of the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.
And we're especially pleased and honored today to have with us both Mr. Simeon Booker on the right on the screen and Mr. Moses Newson.
And I'm here to gentlemen with long histories of engagement with the Civil Rights era and beyond and before as journalists.
So Mr. Newson, Mr. Booker, thank you very much for troubling to make the trip here today and sit down. Thank you.
Good to be here.
I thought I might start Mr. Booker with just having you tell us a little bit about your entry into your professional journalistic work when you joined in 1942.
You joined the Afro-American as a reporter at $18 a week.
Well, I'm just trying to think back that floor.
I was quite close to the Afro because the publisher called Murphy and my uncle, Jason Waring, Jr., the principal of Downing Town Industrial School in Pennsylvania, reclasses me to all of it.
And so I always had a yearning for journalism and for the cause of call, Murphy.
And I yearned to go to Harvard because of their joint studies there.
Indeed you'd go to, you would go in the early 50s to Harvard as an event, though.
I did eventually but I started off working as a reporter on the, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, calling post.
Well, the call post, but I went from the Afro to the call post.
Then I applied for a Harvard Neeman and one of Neeman, one of the medical post, when I finished, I then lived in Maya wanted not to go back to call post, but to go to Washington, which I thought would be an event.
But when I talked to the publisher, he said that, uh, come, I'll give you a job and figure this occurred.
I worked in the government as a clerk for a few months till opening came.
But then when the opening came, I found that being at the post, I was way so far down the ladder that all my bad ground experience at Harvard was of no use.
I was a Cuban, like a Cuban poet.
But then I decided to leave and go with Johnny Johnson, who was opening up a small pocket magazine called Jet, and I went to Chicago.
And after a few years, I started to open a Washington bureau, and he named me and started finding the candidate, so I chose myself and came to Washington.
I think that was an excellent hire.
Let me pick that story back up in just a minute, but I want to turn to Mr. Newsson and ask a little bit about your entry into your professional journalistic work.
I know that as a young man, you entered the US Navy and went on from there.
Yes, and after I came out of the Navy, I stuck around a while and did some work with my father.
And I had always been interested in a lot of the newspapers that we got from different places, Pittsburgh, Korea, Chicago, defender, and some of those.
They were telling quite a different story from what we got in the State paper.
At that time, Dynett Flore, most everybody was taking a time union out of Jacksonville.
And I saw a lot of things, a lot of stories that interest me, and being someone who was sort of interested in helping people, and maybe trying to help change the situation we were living on the right time, I chose that as a good feel to go into.
And I started out at Storke College in West Virginia for a while, and then went to the School of Journalism at Lincoln University in Missouri.
And graduated there in the summer of 1952.
And my first job was with the twice-day defender in Memphis.
That was one of the defendants' same papers.
And spent five years there doing some of everything, covered anything and everything that came along.
Sure.
These were years, obviously, when the pace and emphasis of racial change was accelerating, but also meeting lots of early and very unfathomable pediments.
And I want to just ask a little bit about some of the early and substantial stories that you began to cover.
Mr. Newsson, I think when you were in Memphis with the defender, you did work in both 55 in Clinton, excuse me, in Hoxie, Arkansas, and then in 56 in Clinton, Tennessee.
And I wonder if you can recall some of the details of those very early efforts at school this year.
Yeah, those were very interesting entries and entries into the coverage of school desegregation.
At that time, we had heard a lot of things about how difficult it would be and places where there were lots and numbers of black citizens were supposed to be some of the toughest areas.
And places where there were small numbers of black were supposed to be pretty easy situations.
Try not not to be that way.
In Hoxie, actually, a media people were invited to come into the classrooms, ride the buses with the kids, come in, talk to some of the teachers in the classrooms, and that sort of thing.
It was pretty unusual and effective as it didn't happen anywhere else that I went.
It went along pretty smoothly there for a while.
And as you know, there had people who went around trying to stir up problems.
People started to age a cutter and John Kasper.
They got in there after the schools they got started and fired up a lot of people along with KKK and some of the others.
And eventually, they had a lot of problems there.
John was sort of a different story.
At the time, there were about 5,000, maybe 4,000 people in the city.
Only about 200 of them were black.
And sort of a strange situation.
That's a hilly country.
Most of the black people there lived up on what they called Foley Hill.
You went up one way and you drove around the area and you came back down the same way.
They didn't have a high school there for blacks at all.
So the blacks had to go to different counties to go to high school.
And these kids who were going to integrate the school, they had to walk down this hill every morning.
People line up on both sides and yell stuff and throw stuff and that sort of thing.
Back in those days, there was no public accommodation situation.
You had to find some place to stay when you had covered these stories.
My situation in this case is that I was standing over in Knoxville, which is about 18 miles away.
Every evening after things took place, I'd head back out to Knoxville.
That's when the people would come down from the hills and they'd be shooting up guns and they'd be shooting off our crackers and trying to intimidate people.
That sort of thing.
There were a lot of trouble inside the school, but eventually it worked out and then it got bad.
There was a minister just to let you know how bad there was.
There was a white minister who walked down the hill one day with these kids and he lost his job.
He got chased out of town.
Eventually the governor had to call out the National Guard there to bring peace in that situation.
Yeah.
Mr. Booker, I want to ask about...
You were in Chicago in 55 and not yet moved to DC, I think.
Is that right?
That's right.
When you first made your trip down, I think your first trip to Mississippi as I have read was to go down and to cover the work of two gentlemen, Gus Lee and Mr. George Lee,
Pastor Lee, who were doing voter registration work in Humphrey's County, Mrs. Lee.
When I went down, Emmett Till was some Chicago, many Till.
When he was killed, I decided to never make a terrific story for Jit.
I was told the photographer and the self decide we would go down.
To check out, I never didn't.
I was born in Baltimore, grew up in Young Sound of High, and never covered ourselves at all.
So going into Mississippi was completely new to me.
We went down to check on his death, how the two men had gone in and killed him because he whistled it.
I don't know if it was one of the wives, and we went down for that.
The silo kit was different from what I expected.
You also, I think, had developed a very close journalistic connection to Mrs. Till, maybe Till Brown.
When I was with her, we went, remember being with her, when we stayed up all night,
and when we were in the body, we came in from Mississippi, and when it did come, she demanded that the body be open.
So the world could see what they did to my boy.
When they opened the clasket in the funeral, I remember a piece of his skull fell off, and my photographer went over and picked it up and put it back on before he shot a picture.
It was a very crucial scene, but she was a tough lady.
Let me ask you many questions about coming up that theme, but I wanted to ask about your photographer, David Jackson.
He was very good, a very fun photographer, and he could handle all of the murder cases that came up.
And those days the cameras were big. They went a little way to put in your pocket.
So there was a very dangerous thing to be a photographer, and to work in the silo.
And he was a pretty brave fellow. He just dared to do anything.
He was thinking about the till case and about school desegregation. I'm interested in hearing from both of you thoughts about how the black press was evolving in the mid-50s.
54, it's been a very tough year without recession and a lot of retrenchment in circulation figures for a lot of black newspapers.
And then these stories pay the press forward in certain new ways. I'm interested in your thoughts about that.
The jet circle just took off when they ran the picture. They had the reprint.
First time they ever reprinted jet magazines, and there were a lot of interest in that case.
The whole entire black community was becoming aware of the need to do something about it.
Yeah, I think starting with the school ruling in 1954, South was always a pretty tough place.
And places like Mississippi were just backwards, raceless baking.
And we got this real hateful climate where people in the Congress and other leaders were speaking forcefully about the fact that they were not going to integrate schools.
And we were having a lot of problems. You mentioned George Lee, one of the guys who was killed just for trying to get black folks to register the vote.
He was actually one of two people who killed in 1954, just before, in 1955, just before Emmett Till was killed.
And the thing about these murders is that nobody was being convicted. And neither of those two cases, nobody was convicted.
I went down for the funeral of George Lee. And strangely enough, a lot of people went down because that was one of the first times that Roy Wilkins had taken over as head of the NAACP's operation body.
And people wanted to see how tough he was going to be, how strong he was going to be down in Mississippi.
But I think Mississippi had a reputation for being one of the worst places.
And you're asking about the media, the two papers in Mississippi and Jackson, Mississippi.
To my mind were some of the worst. There were a lot of bad ones as far as coverage of civil rights was concerned.
But they were two of the worst. The entire climate, not just the people being killed during the slightest type of things, the case with Emmett Till.
He's supposed to have whistled at some woman, Bryant, who ran a store with her husband Roy.
It happened that they were out of town. The husband was out of town. And he's had brother, mylam, ZW Mylam, were out of town.
They hadn't heard about that thing until one of Till's young friends mentioned it.
So as soon as we heard about him being missing, that he had possibly whistled at a white woman, I went down and shot some pictures around.
His little whistled stop place, four or five stores, and pretty much nothing else.
I interviewed grandfather at a cotton field where he was doing some work there.
He really wanted to stay down. He said that was going to be one of his most profitable years.
He was a chef woman with this German guy. But his wife left immediately. I hated back to Chicago.
It didn't take long in those days to get a trial on the way. We just finished something that went on for three years.
I think they killed him around August 28th or something like that. And we were down there for the trial on September 19th.
So that was very short period.
To me, I guess I was about 28 at the time. It was a pretty tough situation down there.
Some of the guys were more veteran, so I had a little different.
But it was a pretty tense situation for me. I had gone down early and interviewed this year.
George Smith, who's actually made the arrest.
When we got over, he was someone you could talk to, you could interview.
When we got over, whether the trial was being held, or when Tallah had a county, a different story.
We ran it to Sheriff's Trader. He hadn't done much of a job.
I was trying to get witnesses to do something in the case.
I guess I was selected one day to go out and try to with some NAAC people to see if we could round up some witnesses who would be there.
I actually sure was going to testify and did testify on behalf of the guys who had done the murder.
We changed clothes and went out wearing something, something like plantation workers would use to be wearing.
We did round up a couple of people who did testify on the case.
I think it was important. The NAACP was pretty much the hell end of the case.
There were three people who went along the wall in NAACP. Our driver was Megga Evers, who drove us to all those bank-bite plantations and plantings where we were trying to find witnesses back there.
I was quite interested. Later, I think that night, some of the other press guys, Black and White, went out with police officers and they made arrangements to have a couple of people testify on the trial.
Let's pause here.
We're back after a short break. Mr. Newsom, you were talking about some of the strategies and approaches you used in and around money,
especially during the trial. For example, changing clothes and going out to search for witnesses in that very unusual and exceptional situation.
I'd be interested in having both of you talk a little bit about generally how your ideas and strategies for going into communities in very tense situations as Black reporters and doing work in very tense and potentially dangerous situations.
We just started a string of systems and that was in all the rural areas and so we had people who would submit articles or ideas every week and we would pay for the best one.
These people now only became informers for the article, but they also became informers for new developing and guides when we were coming to their community center for the recording.
We developed a huge new audience in an area that had been forgotten and I remember many times when these special stringers became the real source of new jet carrier students.
We were the center of the talk and the party and this stringer would lead them around the community to where they wouldn't be hurt and they could come up with exclusive news which kept jet full.
We also had a column, a weekly column and jitter, take a tape where I could run two or three senses about little events that happened all across the country.
I used this to carry more information that these stringers would send up that never got a new figure until jet ran and it amazed me how the community sort of ignited.
It lit up over and it was very valuable.
We had the stringer system too, I guess most of the publications did at that time because you didn't have a lot of bureaus in those places because we were so close to Mississippi, we were ending out of there and all for a lot.
When I talk about the culture down there, I think the till case was a good example of the kind of culture you ran into when you were covering those kind of stories.
I think a lot of the guys changed clothes quite often when they were down there.
The search for witnesses was the only time that I had changed clothes. I always went the way I worked when I was at the office around town.
But you ran into the situation where a lot of people were very helpful, some people were scared to talk, you know, their jobs were at stake and that sort of thing.
People were somewhat beaten down because of the system.
For example, of course it was not just little people on the street who would do things or say things who would actually kill people sometimes.
A lot of bodies were being found and people were actually afraid.
But the entire system worked that way.
The courthouse where they were having a till trial, of course it was segregated, you know, most of them were.
But how did the press operate? The sheriff told us when we got there, there had been no integration in my courthouse.
In addition to that, there was a press table there for white reporters and photographers and whatnot.
But not for black reporters. We were as often as the case to sit in the audience and that sort of thing.
Well, it happened that Congressman Charles Diggs from Detroit had come down as an observer.
And he and some of the veteran reporters complained to the judge about the situation.
So eventually they did set up a table off to the side where reporters could work.
And some of the other people were there, lawyers and whatnot, set at the same table over there.
So that was a sort of condition that you worked on everywhere.
You could hear what you could hear.
I remember covering a case, rape case, where some white women involved.
They had raped a co-ed on a tala haze, the University of Florida, A&M.
And most of the time I was sitting up in the balcony trying to hear as best you could.
But quite often that was just a situation.
Every single facet of life was pretty much segregated.
But you went out there to do a job.
And most of us thought that it was very important because newspapers had a way of writing what they wanted to write and leaving out what they wanted to leave out.
The first time I saw a story about Till being killed, I was probably two or three answers in the commercial appeal on a press semester, one of the two there in Memphis.
Once you get down there, it's a little different situation.
I was just a Paul that I afraid people were to talk about the situation.
That's a good reason.
Let me ask you both about what memories especially come to your mind when you think about the work you did covering Little Rock in 57.
We were out at Little Rock very early with a team, a photographer, and we stayed on a case.
I got to know all the kids, the parents, even before the story broke like it did.
I think that's good to know stories like that and then write it so that people could get an idea of who these people were, what they were going through.
Rather than say six kids showed up at the school, you got a chance to go to the inside and how the community grow to help them keep up them around.
Another thing that opened a white and a bureau, and I was very unusual those days, and we saw a big bureau that we covered Congress,
we covered the different government departments, the program, and state governments, and government legislation.
We did a lot of material that gave us enough material to fill our magazine and to cover with unusual ideas for everything.
Little Rock turned out to be one of the most important of all the civil rights cases.
It was sort of a long drawn out sort of a situation.
First off, arrangements had been made for the nine youngsters who were selected to integrate the school.
And on the verge of the day when they were supposed to enter school, government fathers changed his mind and said school was not going to be integrated.
And to see that his orders were carried out, he called out the National Guard.
My first day over there, I was walking across Park, school was located there, Park in 16th.
And I was met by Colonel who came out and greeted me and told me that I wouldn't be able to work up there because of my very presence might result in problems.
Now they had a bunch of white reporters over there and photographers and all that sort of thing.
But to make sure that I got his message, he had some of his troops to escort me out of the area, back to my car.
And as it happened, you always pick up a couple of guys who don't follow you with all kinds of threats and that sort of thing.
It was just two of them.
So I went to her about them.
And I had a camera and a strobe unit and that sort of thing.
But this situation in Lillrock, as Booker was explaining, we spent a lot of time hanging around the home of LC and Daisy Bates.
Mrs. Bates was head of the NAACP and she was the one who was actually working closest with the nine students.
And we'd hang around that paper, hang around the home, the kid would come in and dance and doing what kids do, reading or refrigerator and that sort of thing.
So you did get to know them pretty well.
Next time we were up there when this kid was supposed to go to school, we bumped into this big crowd of people who were lined up on the streets out there.
And they were four of us, myself and the LLX Wilson, who had been my boss at the Tri-State Defender.
This was my first story for the Afro-American newspapers in Baltimore.
And as we went up, the mob was sent in and where you guys are going and you're never going to get back from up there and this kind of stuff.
And we were putting up ID cards and that kind of stuff.
It didn't mean anything and they told you that doesn't mean anything.
You'd put that egg in, you know, they were calling all kinds of names and that sort of thing.
So eventually, someone from up front yelled that the kids were getting into the school.
They had come around another way and that's when all hell broke loose.
They started attacking us.
And I suppose you've seen some pictures of LLX Wilson getting kicked and beat up and guys climbing on his back and hitting him with brakes and that sort of thing.
I was sort of walking at that time with Jimi Hicks with the Amtadown News at the time.
We sort of ran along to stay out of the way of these guys.
We just took a few leaks, you know, that sort of thing.
But LLX Wilson, I had worked with him for five years at the Defender and I was trying to encourage him to come along with us.
But it turned out that LLX Wilson had had a problem with the KKK down in Leesburg, Florida, where I had gone to school after I reached the senior level.
I didn't know Mr. Wilson but we rode two and from work a lot of times down there and ran a little incident one evening when
we had stopped at it. I was house there and problem came up.
And after that some guy was waving and going, I mean he just walked slowly along and I didn't know what was going on or what the situation was.
So I jumped out and sort of interceded and told the guy we were leaving and getting away.
But that was the first time that he told me that he had run into problems with the KKK down in Leesburg.
And he had run and he made a place to himself that never again would he run under that sort of a situation.
So that's why he wouldn't run at LLX and that's why he got beat up pretty badly.
And his wife, Imaging, she still thinks that Beaton he took there, sort of hasten his early demise.
But the reason I say that that was one of the most important of all the civil rights cases that after they attacked us that day with the NAACP and others complaining about the fact that we weren't getting away.
And then he had no protection down there.
President Eisenhower decided to send in the military.
And what that meant was that no more would people be able to use violence to actually prevent desegregation activities from taking place.
As a matter of fact, I thought we would never see that sort of a situation again.
But later as I found out and going down to Mississippi, the case of James Meredith, people were still trying to do it the violent way.
But that was an extremely important case and it meant that people would have protection both reporters, kids who were trying to get into these schools.
There were some of the bravest kids that all over the country. They were absolutely fantastic and people would say, why are you going out there?
These kids would go out there. You had to be there too.
One of the stories I always look back on is one morning when those kids weren't supposed to go to school.
One of them didn't get the word Elizabeth Eggford.
And she got up there by herself and the guard wouldn't let her through.
I think at first she thought there would be friends of hers.
But she realized eventually that they weren't.
And she started to leave in a group of white people surrounding her and just gave her a hard time, absolutely.
And we weren't up there because they weren't supposed to be there that day.
And as soon as I heard about it, I went out to a house and was talking to her.
And she said something that a 15-year-old kid would say, I never thought people could be so cruel.
And I made it to the leader of a story. It got played in the paper.
Someone else also did a very good story on it.
But those were the kind of things you would run into out there.
And from time to time, you just had to stop writing and just listen to people talking about what they went through as individuals out there trying to just get an education.
Okay, we're back on after that. They're short break.
I want to ask you both about, before we turn to the freedom ride, I want to ask you both about, as far as you can recall, what was your mood about the prospects for race relations, say by the, just, just the early 60s?
Canadi has been elected there in the fall of 60.
But you'd seen things like Little Rock plus and minuses. I guess the pluses that Eisenhower exerted federal authority.
But minuses are pretty tough situations still. And do you recall what you moved about the prospects for race relations work?
Well, Eisenhower, he just, he came to civil rights with a blank. I remember after he went out of office, I went over the interview and had a retirement.
And he said to me, all the questions, you asked me all of them on civil rights. And I said, now my opportunity.
I said, well, that was the one subject you never talked about, what are your questions?
You always never came out. I could, Kennedy, crazy, started it. He got going. And then unfortunately, he got killed.
And so the different, I was named a Paul Barrett at his funeral, something on a early November day.
But he really opened it up to the press. I had a season of second row. He really, now I'm just talking.
But he did play to show back your part of this too.
Mr. Newton, you remember your, your moved around the time of Kennedy's election?
Yeah, I think everybody sort of expected somewhat more than what was actually done.
They, they set a good mood with some of the speeches they were making and, and that sort of thing, which was good for the country,
because there had to be another voice out there beside what some of the media were doing and what some of the seven lawmakers were doing.
And what they were saying, you know, about pulling out of the union and disobeying laws and that kind of stuff.
We had a lot of different organizations working tirelessly, you know, the NACP and Urban League and core, the young people in SNCC.
Some of the most encouraging thing was some of the courts, some of the judges who started making some very important rulings, knocking down Jim Probe, Barriers, Johnson, Warrant and some of the others,
who were very, very important in setting the stage for some of the progress that would take place later.
All these guys, all these things were encouraging.
I don't know if anybody saw the changes coming, the way they eventually came about as earlier because,
you know, people who talk about the 50s and the 60s, but people had been fighting the long, long time, this struggle had been going on for ages.
People were getting killed out there. We had a family in Old Florida get done about it doing it on holiday season, Christmas holiday season.
So it was not just that one period, but I do believe that when they killed Emmett Till, supposedly for whistling a white woman,
I think people took sort of a different attitude. Now they killed our kids, and kids also took a different attitude.
I think a lot of the young people began to become more assertive, more active.
A lot of adults became more active in putting themselves on the line to help bring about some of the changes that would take place.
People really don't know about a lot of the activities that were taking place, a lot of the prices that people paid.
I remember being in a little church greeting movement down in Mississippi, not too far from where money was located.
And we had people inside, including some of the top civil rights people, and the speaker there was professor at Howard University.
And outside you have the police, KKK and other student people's pictures. They were doing that so that they could kick people off the plantations and fire them and that kind of stuff.
And during the meeting, we had another one of those moments where people sang songs about not letting them turn around, turn them around.
And after we sang somebody would get up and talk about an experience that they had.
And eventually this guy, I guess it was middle-aged guy, something he gets up and he was telling them about his situation.
And the situation was that he had been on this farm for ages, Shackropper.
And he had gone over to try to register vote.
And now the owner was telling him that he had a few days to find someplace to go.
He's got this family, several kids, he's got no job, no transportation, no access to places to go.
And he tells these people, don't do anything for me, don't worry about me. Just get out there and try to register and vote.
Man, it was one of those moments that you have out there.
They raised money for the guy at James Farm, it was there and some other one they would say that more money would be coming.
But that was the kind of pressure these people were actually living under.
You know how to pull these and fire trucks running up and down outside the church with the bells clanging and ringing and shooting people's pitches so they could turn them over to the bosses.
And people were getting fired up and right. People with no money, no funds, no place to go.
So they were paying a real heavy price now.
And you didn't hear about those stories a lot of times, but they were going on.
And some of the bravest people out there were guys like Moses, sneak guys who would sell down in these little towns and stay for weeks.
You know, I grew out here on a story and things cooled off a little bit.
You know, I was gone back to Baltimore, but these people were there day in and day out.
And I don't know how some of them did it.
I'm going to ask you both about an experience where you were very, very close to some very, very tough history, which was the Freedom Ride.
And I'm interested if you can think back about how each of you first was asked to consider participating in the bus ride as a journalist.
Do you remember who first reached out to you or how the...
Well, on the Freedom Ride, I went to Baltimore and said, look, I want to go with you to see what happens with a photographer.
And we went, not as a participant, but as a bluerbist.
But I don't know if there was any difference, because people didn't take time to say he's a bluerbist or a participant.
And that was an eye out.
And we went all the way.
We went from Washington after the Selma and Natty Era, when one bus was burned and the motor was on that bus.
I was on the other bus.
We got to Birmingham, I looked at the window and I would see this crowd, if you would change and all that kind of stuff.
I ducked out the back of the bus and luckily hail the black cab driver who took me to take a gun.
You remember the shuttle was time?
The shuttle was time.
And the call candidate's office and said, man, you got to get out of here.
These people in trouble.
And they said, well, you saved life.
I'm going to go on that for a second there.
That was a real experience.
But my contribution was not whole.
I'm just finishing the book.
My experience is on the front line.
And another two or three months I hope to be able to take it to an agent and say, look, come and get this problem.
But again, I put in a lot of material.
It's not an agent book on the rise of blacks.
Because I was in many different events and at different angles.
But you could see a lot of problems.
You didn't see from this area.
But you saw over here.
And one follow up on, because you were in DC as bureau chief, you were able to forge some relationships with people inside the administration.
I had a lot of contact with him.
And I was in the FBI.
Or I got all close and listen with the presidents, you know, with the administration, the department.
And you could see what you could do.
Plus, I was a slick fellow those days, not anymore.
I was a Westinghouse real commentary three times a week.
So what the black community, I could get over in the white community and do things to explain what black was doing here.
And then really open up a lot of it.
I could see where blacks had a little prayer, a daily prayer.
But you get over in, dropping commentary on something subject with a creative, much stirred, and within the black community.
So I played a lot of kind of games and over there.
I'm too old to do that.
I always just like to work with Simmons Booker because,
you know, you could depend on, you didn't have to worry about some guy trying to, you know, go on out there and say something or doing something that gets you in more trouble than you were already in just being out there.
We got a call from Jim Palmer, even when it's someone to come out two weeks and go on the journey with them.
And I agreed to go.
At the time, I had already accepted invitations to come down to New Orleans to cover voting rights here and that would be inhaled by the Civil Rights Commission.
The day they left on May 4, 1961, I had gone down to do that story and came back and had a few things to do in office.
I didn't catch up with the freedom writers until they were at North Carolina, A&T College.
I just like to mention a little story that I did down in North Carolina.
It's one of those stories that don't get much play.
We had a registrar there who was testifying over and over and over how she would give these little simple tests and all the white people could pass the test, but none of the white people could pass the test.
And that's why none of them were being registered there in that area of Louisiana.
So the lawyers from the Civil Rights Commission, they got to understand and they started asking her some of these simple questions that she said that the black applicants couldn't answer.
And a few of the simple questions.
And she sat there and she couldn't answer any of those questions, not any of them.
And we were trying to be headline all the way across the paper saying that Dixie Voto, Oficial, Flunk's Own Test.
And that's the sort of thing. That's the way things were being done in the South.
But as I caught up with the freedom writers, what they were doing, you know, mixed groups would go all twos and threes at the time and go into these stations to test to see whether they could use the facilities and that sort of thing.
I guess I shouldn't go through a long story, but there had been three rulings that made it possible for them to do this.
Courage tried it back in 47 and didn't get too far because they really didn't have the legal support.
And before then, there was a woman out of Baltimore who was coming out of Virginia and she refused to give up her seat.
So she won a case in 1946 that dealt with the interior travel.
After that, there was the Rose Park situation about 10 years later. The Rose Park situation down in Montgomery.
And eventually four women represented, Turner Fred Gray. Neither of them was Mrs. Poggs who was arrested, led to this famous boycott over a year long.
And I have this most incredible thing. The world I've never seen anything like that in the United States where these people got together and refused to ride the buses for that sort of period.
But these four women who were plaintiffs in this case, they won an intra travel case.
Then after that, I was a young fellow named Bruce Boynton. He refused to give up his seat in one of the bus stations.
And that resulted in a case that covered facilities. So now you know, you had three things done.
So when I watched them for a while and the first rear blotter, so out there was now Congressman John Lewis.
They got down to the place, Rock Hill, South Carolina. And he went in. A couple of the people went in with him to white people went in with him.
And they got attacked and got thrown out of that place. And Lewis was pretty blood in when he came out.
Shortly after that, when we went at Latter, my Luther King came over. People would have these meetings, you know, with great freedom writers and that sort of thing.
Not everybody was happy about what was going on. But my Luther King had told our good friend, Simon Booker here, and some others that he had heard that the KKKK and others were planning to see the freedom writers never got out of Alabama alive.
And that was a pretty serious situation. So to make matters worse, the day we were going to be leaving for Anderson Alabama, and that bus was going to be leaving to go another route ahead of the Birmingham.
James Palmer learned that his father had died and his mother wanted him to come back right away.
So we had that situation where we didn't have our main leader there, but they were going to push on anyway. I was on the Greyhound bus that day. And I don't know the road.
I know the Greyhound bus hailed us down and told us to put a nice car in my butt at Anderson Alabama station at the Anderson Alabama Greyhound station.
And when we got there, sure enough, it was pretty angry mob there. And they were calling freedom writers all kind of names and, you know, niggas and communists come on out and integrate Alabama and that sort of stuff.
They were beaten on the buses with the bus with chains and sticks and whatever else they had.
The bus driver had to take out the business there. He would lock the door when he got out. So nobody could get on the bus.
And I guess I had another one that was little experiences. There was a woman on the bus that knew nothing about the freedom writers. She was coming home from a funeral.
She was sitting across the aisle from me and she was saying things like, why are they doing this to us? And I don't want to die here like this. And she was down on a knees between the two seats there.
So I go and try to tell her what was going on and sort of thing. And I was still watching the windows. I was still trying to break out the windows there.
And she told me I could use a name in my story. I didn't even remember the homes, I believe. And eventually, the bus driver got back in and we took off.
And at the time we got to the edge of the city. We heard that the sound of tires going down.
And you could look back and you could see a line of cars that were following us. And there was a little road that stayed in front of the bus to keep the bus from picking up speed. So we saw the trap there.
That's when we find out that there were a couple of white state troopers on the bus. We didn't know about it. They were playing clothes. And they started again breaking out windows and banging on the bus and daring people to come out and that sort of thing.
One of these guys, one of the state offices, L. Cowlin, he pulled his pistol and stood in the doorway to keep anybody from getting on the bus. And that's all the save that's right.
They finally made a breakthrough, one of the windows and it threw this fire bomb thing in the seat just behind me, which is an empty seat. And I got a few burns on the back of the ear and that's all the thing. But nothing serious.
Suddenly it was pitch black on that bus and a couple of people got out of the windows and caught rides. Several of us sort of trapped on the bus there until we could get out.
And I said, well, I'm going to be the last guy off this bus and the way it gets trapped on here. So I just put a hack into it with my mouth and nose and that sort of thing and hung around as long as I could.
And it started getting hot on there. It was time to get off. So we got out and I tell you when you step off that bus and you looked around and you saw these people crawling around trying to get there.
And I was trying to get the smoke out of the chairs and people crawling, caw and gag and it was one of those sites that make you wonder why Americans are doing that sort of thing to fellow Americans who was just trying to exercise their rights.
And eventually that bus burned right down, brought open daylight and burned out this expensive Greyhound bus.
By the time I got off and saw these people shooting pictures I realized that I had stuck my camera upon the seat. It's pretty dangerous to be getting off in that situation with a camera on your neck.
It burned up with the bus but I was able to contact the Greyhound company and get the bus back and get the camera back.
It's been all of you now that the New Zealand and Washington where people can see it they want to.
But I was a pretty shaky occasion. The ones of us who were on that bus most of us the ones who didn't get out and catch rise were taken to the hospital there in the city.
And we just saw the stuff there. The young guy who's in charge of the bus in the absence of former Joe Perkins.
He was calling all around trying to get some battery helpers get out of their hospital. They were telling you can't stay here and the police were saying we can only protect you to just sit in line.
It was kind of dark out there. You know, we can hear those people out there still hanging around.
Eventually he reached Revan Schoelsworth, Oven Birmingham. He agreed to send over Caravanne cars to get us out of there.
And while we were waiting around, at the time after America was doing about 13 editions, the National Edition went to press on Sunday nights.
I was able to step outside and get a telephone and call the night editor to tell him what kind of story I would have the next day.
And as him to call my wife and tell her that I was okay. But he's got a tough duty sometimes after.
Let's take a break.
I want to pick up on the day March, May the 14th, 1961.
I'm just so struck by how so close each of you came to the prospect of just very serious injury or death in Aniston.
And then when you stepped off that bus in Birmingham at the terminal, the course people were getting beaten so badly.
And somehow folks just missed catching a look at you before you began that gap.
I wanted to get much of a chance to get this empty show up. I wanted to show it all about going.
But it was a very close moment. I wear it so many close moments.
Because that was part of the life. And you just accepted it.
I wonder, I'm thinking about the stretch of time between the Freedom Ride and the March on Washington those couple of years.
And I remember the speech that John Lewis gave at the March on Washington.
It was full of so much frustration with the government for its reluctance.
The Kennedy administration for its reluctance to step in and aid people in the South who were suffering white violence.
And I'm wondering kind of how each of you felt coming out of an experience like the Freedom Ride and what perspectives you came away with on that question or others.
Just what it looked like you feeling you're thinking.
Well, my anger was the big deeper and coverage of this underclass of blacks.
Opened up some more of them given opportunities.
That's the only way you want to do anything.
People can't get education training. You don't get jobs or this and so with Jeff and Ebony tried to educate and reach them.
By them to send their kids to school, take an interest in education, clean them their health, all those things.
But that's a sort of an inward process.
But it's one that you have to use as a brother to brother to sister for the work.
You know, getting out of press or play is not front page new.
And that's one of the real problems that you have.
I think there was another one of the situations where the ambitions and aspirations of black people didn't exactly coincide with the administration's viewpoints.
How they saw their own jobs and what this kind of thing, how it could affect them in a different way.
There were just so many things that the general public didn't know about.
That reporters were able to learn some of the background about things that Jay Ega Hoover was doing at the Justice Department.
We saw these guys out there, FBI guys watching, but then they would come to you later and ask you what happened.
I'm going to take a lot of new rock. I want to try to get away.
Some guy come later than I had to ask me what took place. And I saw him standing on the sidewalk.
But he, again, not just to keep saying that one person, John Lewis and some of his younger folks weren't too happy with the way that the administration, the candidate administration,
was trying to slow down some of the efforts at bringing about changes.
That became quite an issue there.
But Demart was one of the historic things. I was sort of happy. It didn't happen often, but it was closed by Baltimore.
I took my wife and a neighbor who was a wife of one of our photographers went along and were able to get that seat and take part in that event.
It was a great event. Sometimes you look back on it. You got to hear my Duke Kang a lot of this thing that turned out to be so great.
I don't know over and over a number of times. But when he got a role in that day, the circumstances was so much different.
But all these white union people and church leaders and everybody else bringing themselves together to demand that changes be made, it took on a completely different light.
The impact of it was just great. He's another guy that people don't understand what he was going through a lot of times.
I know, shortly before his death, they were planning the pool of people's mods on Washington.
I went down to Atlanta to interview him. As usual, he was running late and he and Andy Young had to catch a flight after they finally came out of this big meeting with all these people, pool of people in the young Latinos and whatnot.
I had to interview him actually in a car going to the airport. It was kind of different. You got Andy Young there. You got his wife there. You got Harry Bellafonte there.
You're trying to interview him about some of the problems that was going on. You know, there's FBI was taping him and leaking stuff. Some of the civil rights leaders were saying that his position on the wall was causing him to lose sight of what he was doing.
That sort of thing. They were having trouble raising money at the time. He eventually had to ask him what's your reaction to all this and that people were saying that you were failing at what you were supposed to be doing.
He said something that really struck me. He said that when I was surprised to hear, he said, if I'm failing, then you might say according to the way some people look at it, Jesus Christ failed because He got himself hung on the cross.
I think that story ran about the middle of March in the year that he died. It was just a few weeks before he died. It was a strange thing. He was on the lot of stress that a lot of people didn't know and didn't appreciate.
He was struggling with all the charges about the communist associations and all the rumors, the type of stuff that a lot of people had printed before that they started printing and trying to bring him down.
He was quite an interesting guy. He was a brave guy. Not an awful lot of people would have gone through what he went through and kept the front that he kept up there and plugging away as he plugged away day after day.
Mr. Booker, do you have special recollections of Barnard the King and Gawson, to all the work you did covering the movement in River King?
Well, he was very unusual there. I've never seen him just appointed or defeated. He always seemed to be on the make, on the go. I couldn't ever figure out, he never gave up.
He was in a very difficult situation. He always stayed out with a little prayer to himself and he kept on. A lot of people said, oh, he always gone on. He never did. He stayed with...
How did you cover up Malcolm X? No, I didn't. There was an area Malcolm X, Stoke, a whole cry. I never paid much attention to it.
I was like the whole deal was to grab the press attention. They went in, they knew I had grabbed certain sections of it.
The rest was Royal Wilkins, Whitney. I remember Whitney when he was died in somewhere in Europe. I had to fly over to one plane, pick up his body.
I was in Nigeria. I think we went on that flat together. We went down on Air Force One. President Nixon flew down to participate in the services down there for Whitney Young.
Simon and I were among the people who went down to cover that event.
Let me take you back for just a minute. Is there more that you'd like to add about... obviously we could talk for hours on this thing, but are there other things that come to your mind when you think about what we came covering human beings?
No, actually I didn't get to cover him too much. We had a staff in Baltimore and usually when he came to Baltimore he was covered by some of the other staff people there.
I sat in on a lot of the speeches he would make, but I didn't actually cover him. It was fascinating to see him and Abanath they were working together. Abanath would pass the basket and collect the money.
King would make those great speeches that he was known for. But they were quite a tool when they were working together. I was done in Alabama in the Black Belt, there for a while after King died.
Abanath was trying to carry on his work and it just wasn't working the way everyone had hoped it would. But he gave it his best shot at it.
He didn't have the personality that Dr. King had.
Was either of you and other of you covered the Democratic National Convention in Atlantic City in August of 64 with the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party controversy?
I covered four conventions to Republicans, to Democrats, a couple of Miami Beach and New York and that significant one in the Republican one in Kansas and Missouri there when the conservative wing took over the party.
But I didn't do 64.
One more question, then we can take a little break and come back and finish up. I'm interested in your thoughts about evolving relations between Black journalists and white journalists and earliest efforts at beginning now to staff some black journalists on to larger white papers and just pass this period.
I'm interested in your thoughts on the relations between Black press and the White Press.
I thought there was a reason they had different standards. The white press would pick off the prominent black whatever.
The black press, they were kind of local politics and all, but it was a very difficult kind of thing to stand as to where they stand as a fidget holder.
I covered all the conventions, but so long ago I wouldn't remember one of them. My memory is good.
I don't know. I didn't have the usual contact that a lot of the other reporters we had would have.
I was, if I went to Baltimore, I was only on the beat for about a year and then I got moved into the office and won eight inches job, one in a position of another.
Before that, when I was in Memphis, I knew quite a few of the guys. In covering stories, it was somewhat different because normally they would stay at some hotel or something of some motel that would be central headquarters for a lot of them.
We were not able to stay at those places. Some of the guys we got along when we were working, I could answer some things for them sometimes.
They could help me with things, sometimes on meetings that I wasn't able to get to.
By and large, it was a professional relationship I would call it. I didn't do a lot of hanging out with anybody.
In particular, for five years, I spent a lot of time down in Mississippi. They had papers with Karen things which were pretty much opposite to what I was writing and what I was emphasizing.
They were emphasizing something else. Frankly, you didn't know who was who. There was no need to be glad about a lot with people. You didn't know what they were writing, what was going on.
I didn't really go out of my way to try to have a great social relationship with them.
We're back. We're back up there, a little break. We're just going to finish up. Mr. Booker, I want to ask for your thoughts about being print reporters in an era when television came on to really do so much.
I want to do so much to impact the way that the American public at large reacted to the Civil Rights story. Let me just open up with that. Any thoughts or reflections you might have on that question?
I think when the White Press really became involved in covering the Civil Rights story as a movement, nothing greater could have happened.
They had the TV networks and that was just invaluable. They would show how people were being treated. They did some great interviews.
I always had to feel that Americans as a whole, although they were not really anxious to bring up and see the changes that were taking place.
Deep down, there was sort of a feeling in America that justice was important and treating people a certain way was important.
When those screens were showing people being beaten, forced down by hoses and trampled over by horses, I think it had a great impact.
It was something that the Black Press could not do at the time. Some of the coverage shows a great effort to get people thinking a different way.
I think it was very successful. I don't think the movement would have been able to do the things at the speed that it was done without those images.
They were just greatly important to move things to where it is now. The media as a whole have been quite helpful.
I still have some questions sometimes about some of the coverage. I will get into that. It was just a long story. I tell you one example. It was the story involved to profess it up at Harvard and the way it was treated.
This was a disorderly conduct thing that would not have stood up in the court in this country because the court said that American citizens can call a policeman a name. You can yell at a policeman. You can demand to see his ID.
That is all that the sergeant charge him with. Press told us, media told us in great details that the Black Office had seen was 100% behind the sergeant. His command said he was just doing what he was trained to do.
Nobody was emphasizing in mainstream media that this was such a bad arrest that it wouldn't hold up in any court. I mean for decades these rulings had been made quite obviously.
The mainstream press didn't do the job on it. There were a lot of blogs that were doing cable stations. I was talking about New York Times and Washington Post. They wanted to tell them people that this was a case that would not stand up in any court.
Most of them didn't even tell you why the case was dropped. Pigeon said it was dropped and the charges were dropped.
The media has done a great job but from time to time you see covers that some of it's suspect.
That was the professor gates in 2009. I believe it.
Mr. Booker, a final question. I know in 68 following the assassination of Robert Kennedy that you had had connections to the Kennedy's and to Robert Kennedy and I think participated in his funeral.
In 1968 after Bobby Kennedy's death. Did you have recollections of that experience?
Well, I think it was a very sad occasion. I think he was the first official of that right to be sensitive to racial matters and actually did something about it.
Others would talk about it, not publicly to us, but he was very frank and did a lot of things.
But then he got killed and it sort of wiped out. Linda came along completely different in the visual.
He just won. He couldn't accept criticism until he couldn't deal with a whole lot of blacks with different views.
He had to be the boss of anything. So everything ended there. And op-op political structure seemed to disintegrate and we're now trying to rebuild again, which we finally did when Obama came through.
But then it still splitted on the white side. It's not a unity. So I guess America will always be.
I hope that we'll all have a chance to extend our conversation at some point because it's been just wonderful to be with you both. Thank you so much.
Thank you. This has been a presentation of the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.