From the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum of African American History and Culture.
And I'll give a round of applause.
Alright, so today is, I believe, the 11th of May 2013. We're in Seattle, Washington.
You're listening to the voice of David Klein for Virginia Tech.
Also on behalf of the Southern Oil History Program at UNC Chapel Hill.
Today, we are visiting with Aaron Dixon.
And behind the camera today is John Bishop from Media Generation and UCLA.
And this project is, this is the Civil Rights History Project for the Smithsonian's National Museum of African American History and Culture and the Library of Congress.
So I just wanted to say thank you very much for making time for us being part of this project.
Okay, thank you.
And what I'd like to do to start is just start with your childhood, but tell us about the family into which you were born, where and how they may have been put together.
Okay.
Let me see.
My mother, her parents came from Mississippi.
And she was heavily influenced by her great-grandmother, who was born in 1867.
And her mother was a slave.
At some point she got, you know, she became free and she lived a little life of a free woman.
But she was intertwined with the whole history of slavery.
And so her kids, particularly my great-great-grandmother Emma, you know, was born into the whole era of Jim Crow.
And, you know, it was very difficult for her to find work. The only work that Emma could find was at the Laundras.
And she worked for many, many years at the Laundras.
And she had, I believe, seven kids.
I think four of them died, you know, fairly young.
And her husband also died in a tragic accident because I believe he was a breakman.
And so my grandmother, Emma's great-granddaughter, or no, Emma's granddaughter, actually, was a product of a relationship between a Jewish man and her mother.
And from what I understand, her mother was ostracized. This was a Mississippi.
Her mother was ostracized by the rest of the family because she had this relationship.
And so my grandmother's mother passed away when my grandmother was only three years old.
So she really didn't get to know her mother. And she didn't know anything about her father, the Jewish man.
And so eventually she was sent to Chicago to be raised by an aunt, her sisters, one of her mother's sisters.
And then part of the time she was raised by Emma, a good portion of the time she was raised by Emma in Mississippi.
So my grandmother met Roy Sledge, her husband.
And Roy's father was a blacksmith, one of the only few blacksmiths in Mississippi at the time who rode around in a white horse and would understand.
But for himself, he was some independence.
So my grandfather's belief, his mother was half-native American.
So let me see.
So my mother was born to this union of Roy Sledge, who was half-native American.
And her mother, Josephine Sledge, who her birth name was Joe Willie, that was her birth name.
And so they moved to Chicago and it's part of the migration of Blackstone South.
And my mother was raised in Chicago and Milwaukee in St. Paul.
So anyway, my grandfather Roy, he worked as a Pullman Porter, became an alcoholic and at times was a strange from the family.
Eventually he became sober in the States over further remaining years of his life.
And he was able to get a job at the post office where he retired.
Now, my mother, her mother, Josephine, had started her out at playing piano when she was five.
And she became a child prodigy on the piano and began playing costumes which she was seven years old.
And eventually, he would graduate from high school when she was 16.
Then we'll switch to my father's family.
My father's family came from Kentucky.
And his grand actually going back on his mother's side, their family inherited the plantation because of slave owners.
The slave owners had some relationship with my great-great-great-grandmother.
I think they had a relationship.
And so when he left, when slavery ended, he took his family to Denver and he gave the plantation to the woman that he had the relationship with.
And so, and also on my grandfather's side, his grandmother had two great-great-uncles who served in the Civil War.
And when they returned from the Civil War, they actually got land for being in the Civil War.
And they took that land. I'm not unclear where this land was but it was part of the land they got from the plantation.
And they started their own town called Brooksville.
So what side did they fight on?
They fought on the north.
There was some of the first black soldiers to volunteer to fight on the north.
And it goes further back, someone else on that side of the family has traced it back to royalty in Scotland where there's a coat of arms and all that kind of stuff.
So I just remember that my grandmother and my father's son always spoke very proudly of her family and her side of the family.
And in fact, in the house that she lived in in Chicago, they had a lot of furniture that came from that plantation.
And now her father, I'm sorry, her husband, my father's father, was, I think maybe one quarter or maybe half Native American, but he never knew who his mother was.
He was raised by his aunt and his father left and went to St. Louis and became a millionaire.
And so my grandfather, his name was Elmer and my grandmother, Miljert, they met and they married and they moved.
And they had my father was born in Henderson, Kentucky and they moved to Chicago along with that great migration.
And so my grandfather, my father's side, Elmer Dixon, he found work working for a wealthy Jewish man. I'm not sure what capacity.
But he was making enough money where he never allowed his wife to work. His wife never worked.
And so he had my father and he had another daughter, Doris, my aunt. And they were raised in Chicago.
And my father started taking classes at the Art Institute at a young age and he got a scholarship to the Art Institute at a young age.
He was also captain of the ROTC in Chicago. And when World War II broke out, he saw the news at the movie theaters because that's where they had the news at, to movie theaters about the attack on Pearl Harbor.
And he runs down to the induction center and wants to join and he's told that we don't take boys like you.
So when he graduates though, the Army is right there waiting for him. And so he's drafted into the Army along with many of his fellow Black soldiers.
They sent to Mississippi and you know I talk about in my book, there's a lot of stories he talks about in Mississippi and the trials and tribulations of being in such a volatile place.
And as a member of the military and being Black and things get so bad that you know he writes his mother and is telling her what's going on and she writes Elmer Rhodes about.
And you know.
Can you talk this a little bit more about that so what kinds of things we're going on that people are going on?
Yeah sure. Well one of the stories is that their him and his fellow soldiers are out on marching on, I think it's called Dipwreck.
And they're out marching in the hot sun and the hot humid Mississippi sun and they come across this farm.
They want to march across the farm so they won't have to go through the swamp.
And the White Officer asked the farmer if they could march across the farm, his field and the White farmer pointed shotgun at the soldiers and says no niggers are going to march across my field.
So they have to go through the swamps. But when they camp down that night my father and some of his friends go back and burn down the barn of the farmer.
Another story is that he meets a very light, conflicted woman in the small town near the base.
And you know in the deep south you know where they don't know who you are it becomes very dangerous.
And so he wants on their date they're out and he wants to walk her back across town home and she says no you know you probably shouldn't do that.
But you know being from Chicago you know the whole gentleman thing that's what you're supposed to do.
So he convinces her that that's what he's going to do and he's got a uniform on. So he walks her across town he's getting a lot of stairs at people.
And this white sergeant stops him and tells him you know boy when I come back through here you better not be here.
And so no you ask him why he's here what are you doing he says you know I'm walking my friend home he said well you better not be here when I get back.
So my father stops off at the post office on his way to walk her home and he writes his mother and tells the mother that his life is in danger.
So he continues walking her home and just you know fortunate that he didn't run into this sergeant and he makes it back to the base.
And this is another person in the army this is an even a local guy that's harassing him.
Oh this is the police. This is the town sheriff.
So the final incident was that I'm sure there are many others but him and his fellow soldiers were preparing to go on on furlough for the weekend.
And the sergeant comes in and tells him that their furlough is canceled that they have to clean.
And so they refuse to do that and they start to riot and start drawing everything out onto the courtyard.
And this riot lasts for quite a while and finally they bring a train in and they ship them out.
And then my father finally goes to the Pacific theater.
Fights in the Philippines, fights in Okinawa.
While in Okinawa he sees a Marine cut the breast off over dead Japanese woman and hold it up in the air.
And my father just got lost control and grabbed his gun and was going to shoot this Marine.
But he stopped by you know his fellow comrades stopping from doing it.
And so after that incident he goes AWOL.
And he meets a Japanese family and I believe it was in Korea.
And he spends time with them and then he comes back.
And then he is sent back home.
And you know that changed his perspective of his nation, that incident, seeing what the Marine did.
And he started you know seeking out other things and he started being involved in Paul Robuson's youth brigade and starts you know flirting with the Communist Party.
I don't think he actually joined the Communist Party but you know he's flirting with the Communist Party.
So he gets out of the Army and he meets my mother.
They get married and he's a student at a junior college eventually goes to the Orange Institute and graduates.
And my mother has started teachers college and they started having kids.
And so my father gets a job at Shannu Air Force Base as a technical illustrator.
So the family moves to Champaign Illinois and we lived there for maybe about four years or so.
And there is a time I do remember when some men and black suits came to visit my father.
He didn't let him in the house. I'm assuming they were the FBI.
And then he gets a job offer.
I get several job offers and one of them is from Boeing and Seattle.
He remembers Seattle when he came through on this way back from the war and on this way to the war.
He spent time in Seattle.
So he thought it would be a good place to move his family.
So we moved to Seattle. I believe in 57, 58.
And we move around.
So the black community in Seattle gets larger during the war, right?
Yeah, it does.
People coming in to work at Todd Shipyards, blacks coming in.
California, they're coming in to work in the munitions factories.
They're coming up here to work in airplane war factories.
And that's when a lot of black people do start coming west, is during the war.
We're back.
We'll take your parts of town. We're black folks.
Yeah, it would mainly the central area.
The central area was primarily where black people lived.
So with Chinese and Filipinos and Japanese and some Native Americans.
Pretty much were all grouped up in this central area.
And we see my parents.
We finally found a house that we were going to settle down in.
My parents brought a house in Majona neighborhood.
How did you describe that neighborhood?
Majona was a neighborhood of big old houses, lots of trees.
It's just really a really beautiful neighborhood.
It's connected to a series of other neighborhoods.
There's Harrison Valley. There's Majona.
There's Les Chi. There's Mount Baker.
And these are really nice neighborhoods.
And the lake is to the west, to the east.
So we've got views of the mountain, of the lake.
Not far from downtown.
It's really, it was very, really nice growing up in that neighborhood.
And all those other neighborhoods, predominantly black, Filipino, Japanese, and Chinese.
All the grocery stores were all Chinese owned.
The little small grocery stores.
And they gave credit to everybody.
And we all went to school together.
All the Japanese, Filipino, and Chinese.
So growing up, it was almost like we didn't, it wasn't any distinction between our nationalities almost.
And then there were whites that still, that hadn't fled to Bellevue to the east side and other places that had stayed there.
And so it was, it was a, and those whites who had stayed were whites that had decided that they weren't going to move.
They were going to just kind of participate in this new thing that was happening.
You know, you're bringing your classes, those kids would be in your class.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
So it was really, we were really, very fortunate to grow up in that type of environment.
Now outside of those neighborhoods, you know, there was the usual racism.
You know, there was a police brutality.
There was a difficulty with finding jobs.
You know, my mother had a difficult time finding a job.
She had doors closed, closed on her.
Because of race.
Did you remember any particular?
Frederick and Nelson's, the store called Frederick and Nelson.
It's owned by Macy's now, but it was the main retail store, the largest retail store in Seattle, Frederick and Nelson's.
And she had a difficult time.
She was, you know, winning there one time when they had a sign open hiring.
And you know, she was told we're not hiring, you know.
So, but eventually she did get a job, you know.
And, you know, we, growing up, we lived right across the street from a park.
And the park was, had people there, you know, during the summertime.
And there was a lot of different programs.
And because, you know, there's the baby boom generation.
Just a lot of kids.
And people had big families.
You know, I'm talking about, our family was considerably small with four kids, you know.
Two brothers and a sister and myself.
But, you know, there were families that had like seven, eight kids, you know.
Big kids, I mean, big families.
And, you know, almost all of them were two parent families, you know.
And hard working, hard working parents.
And many of them had come from the south and other parts.
And so, and my father being an artist and my father, you know,
he loved other people of other cultures.
You know, he just felt the need to always connect with people of other cultures.
And so, in doing so, he met some artists and people who were in the theater and other art.
And he got involved in the folk dancing group.
And they had a folk dancing group.
And it was, you know, people of, you know, Greek, Jewish, Italian, and Black.
And, you know, they met at different people's homes to do their dancing.
And they met at our house quite often.
You know, I pulled the rug back and bring the wine out.
And the music and they were doing their folk dancing.
So, you know, this is kind of an environment we grew up in.
And all of us kids, we were required to play an instrument.
You know, all the kids were required to play an instrument.
This was my grandmother in Chicago.
My mother's mother, she was a very kind of dominating, kind of controlling type of woman, you know.
And so, she bought the instruments for everybody.
Everybody was going to play something.
And I was told I was going to play the violin.
So, not that I didn't like the violin I did, but I just never quite could grasp the whole reading notes and everything.
And I bought my violin home and it was broken one day.
And so, that was it for me.
My younger brother, he took up the violin.
He played it all the way through to a guy away from high school.
Elmer played the trumpet.
He started out with the guitar.
And he played the trumpet all the way.
And my sister played the piano.
So, my mother often played the piano.
And my father was, you know, trying to do his artwork on the side sometimes.
And he did have the showing of his artwork.
The Fry museum.
So, he was an illustrator, right?
Yeah, he was a technical illustrator.
And his friend, that boy who worked with him, they said he was the best artist out there.
So, but I know that he was really frustrated that he really didn't have the time,
the large amount of time that is needed to just really work on your art.
But he also was a poet as well.
And he wrote poetry.
And he exposed us to poetry.
You know, I learned Shakespeare from my father.
You know, I could quote different parts of Shakespeare because my father was doing it.
So, you know, we also participated in sports.
You know, my father didn't really push sports.
So, we kind of, you know, because we lived across the street from the park,
you know, we were very much involved in football, baseball, basketball, tennis.
We played a lot of tennis.
My brother, Michael, he played.
He got a scholarship to UCLA to play tennis and ping pong and all those things.
And we played in the tournaments with the Parks Department.
And then would there be incidents there playing on sports teams in terms of race at all?
Yeah, yeah, I mean, but there was, I mean, there was always fights amongst each other.
There was so many kids.
You know, there was always the fights, you know, we got in the fights.
But when we were on the softball team and we went to other areas like Ballard, Queen Anne,
to say play other softball teams, yeah, there was a lot of tension and a lot of, you know,
calls going the wrong way.
And there was, yeah, there was a lot of, and people, black people didn't even go to Ballard.
You couldn't really go to Ballard.
Go to Queen Anne, you know, that was, that was unforbidden territory, particularly if you were young.
And even in high school, you know, you know, they turned into, in the fights and almost riots between, you know,
some of those schools Ballard and Queen Anne.
So, yeah, it was, it was, it was really extremely racially charged.
A lot of times, you know, playing some of those teams.
And so, you know, even though we were in this cocoon, you know, there was always that element outside that racism that we always knew about,
and we always heard about, you know.
Did you remember your folks talking to you about what it meant to be black or sort of how your own race consciousness to go?
Well, you know, we...
The artists were defined that long.
Yeah, well, you know, they never really, they just told stories.
They told stories, you know, that oral tradition.
You know, we got the stories from my grandparents, and we got stories from my great grandparents in our aunts,
and our uncles, whenever we were back Chicago, we were constantly hearing stories, and they were constantly telling us all the time.
And when they were talking amongst themselves, we would hear stories, you know, always, you know, this racism and things that are going on.
But I never, our parents never just directly said, this is that, and this is what's going on.
You know, but, you know, we were able to understand.
I remember when I was 13, and I said, I wanted to be a policeman.
My parents got real angry and said, no, you're not going to be no policeman.
And I remember when I was 16 years old, and I said, I wanted to join the Marine and go into Vietnam.
And my father got angry.
I was angry as I've ever seen him, saying that, you know, no son of his is going to go to Vietnam.
And there were, you know, people going, being drafted to go to Vietnam all the time.
You know, a lot of people that we knew were in Vietnam.
So, his own experience.
His own experience. His own experience.
And so.
And have they involved you in politics at all, or I think wasn't there a visit when King came to town when you were in the city?
Yeah, yeah.
You know, we had, you know, political discussions.
We just had discussions in the kitchen.
The kitchen was always the place where we had this guy.
And the older we got, the more broader they got, and the more volatile they got.
And so, let me see, when I was, you know, around 12 or 13 years old, I marched with Martin with the King when he came to Seattle.
Then I started getting involved in the demonstrations around town.
You know, I remember when George Wallace came to town, you know, we demonstrated against that.
And some other things.
And I was only like 12 or 13 or 14 years old.
So, I was only one of my brothers and sisters.
They weren't. I'm not sure how that happened, how I got involved, but I did.
I think it might have been through our church or something like that.
So, I graduated from high school in 1967 by the skin of my teeth.
And I had started working when I was a junior in high school.
I worked four times job. I worked and during the summer, I worked 14 hours a day.
Seven days a week. I bought my own clothes. I bought my own records.
I bought, I was determined I was going to be independent.
And so, I was added, I had a job and I didn't mind working, you know.
And even before that, you know, we are, most of us, my generation, we cut grass.
You know, we went to people's houses, we cut grass.
You know, I had a paper route when I was in middle school, I had in this seventh grade.
I had a paper route. We had to get up at six o'clock every morning and to go deliver papers.
And that was, it became too tough and too much of a strain.
I only had that for a month. But I almost got an evening paper route job.
He did after he came home from school. And so, I had to help him with that.
And he had that for a year.
Oh, right now.
Right now.
No, you know.
You know, hear about that.
Yeah, yeah, that's right.
So, yeah, I graduated and then I was trying to, you know, figure out what I was going to do.
You know, my parents had always told us we were going to go to college.
But I hadn't had any prospects yet.
I wanted to go to Tennessee State.
And, you know, that's where my aunt went.
And most people, my age and older, were going to black colleges.
That's where their destination was.
And that's where I wanted to go to school.
But my grades weren't good enough to get in Tennessee State.
So, I was turned down.
So, I started.
And when Stokeley Carmichael came to town, I really got fired up.
You know, I, and I think Elmer was with me and my great friend, Michael Dean.
And then I started wearing those Stokeley Carmichael glasses.
I started, you know, really, really evolving and really growing in my understanding of what the racial politics was in America.
Would that have been when you first heard the term black power?
Yeah.
Why I'd heard it in the news.
But then this, you know, he had been traveling around the country him and H. Rat Brown.
And then, you know, wow, he's coming to Seattle.
So, I made sure I was here.
And that really changed that, that's just like blew us into another direction, you know.
You really start thinking about press all these things are going on in America, you know.
The riot in, or Los Angeles in 1965.
Right.
And, you know, the continuous riots after that every summer.
And the whole civil rights movement and everything that's going on.
Not to mention that John F. Kennedy had been assassinated.
And as was my father cried when that happened when he was assassinated.
And, you know, really, what's devastating to the black community because the first time we had a president at that really stood up and was going to support the black people was doing.
So, was his picture up in there in their home?
Yeah, I'm sure that, yeah, they had some kind of pictures somewhere.
They had, you see, I'm kind of picture.
Well, there was artwork on the one with some of my father's artwork and other artwork.
And there was a bus to Beethoven who we later found out was, you know, was black.
So, well, we did listen to a lot of Paul Robison.
Paul Robison, what's his name and other Harlem, that Congressman.
Oh, power.
Yeah, yeah.
And records of Martin Luther King.
And we listened to a lot of opera, a lot of musicals, a lot of classical music, a lot of jazz.
You know, there was music. It was a big part of our family.
You know, it was always being played in the house.
So, let me see.
Yeah, yeah.
So, after, after, after, stokely, that's it.
You know, I'm all fired up.
So, I met my job one day and I have, I have my Ray Bans sunglasses on and I'm wearing them on the job.
And my afros getting bigger.
And I worked on this line, this kind of, it was a conveyor belt and everybody, you know, had to put dishes on the trays.
And I had to call them out, you know, what was, it was, you know, sugar-free or whatever type of diet it was.
And I messed up a couple of times as I had my son, Razzlebone.
And so, the supervisor tells me to take my sunglasses off.
Oh, why did she tell me that? I just blew up and I lit into her with all these profanities and walked off my job.
I had that job for about three years.
And so, now, you know, I don't have a job. I'm not a school. I'm hanging out with my friends.
My mother tells me, you know, I got to do something.
So, I found a little part-time job working with a poverty program that was going around doing these racially racial skits.
And so, we're going like the schools and the programs and the different places and, you know, we play these different roles.
And then from that, I met this guy who was a playwright named Aaron Dumas and he had written a play.
And so, he asked me to be in his play. It's called General's Coo.
It was about a craze. It was about a black army that has raised up and they marched on the capital and they started taking over the country.
And they take over the White House and the General gets crazy and I'm his rational son.
And we play this play all over in coffee houses. Where they had coffee houses.
Where they still got coffee houses, but they were bigger than there.
Coffee houses and, you know, in schools, we were doing this play.
And I really started getting into it, you know.
So, then after that, we finished with that, I got into another play called Tom Jones.
And so, I'm also writing poetry. I'm also writing a lot of poetry.
You know, I'm getting into the theater. I do a poetry reading at the Lynx Fine Arts program.
I went to scholarship, $500 scholarship.
And I meet this, I hear about this program from this Jewish woman named Mrs. Richmond.
I went to school with her daughter. She works with the Urban League and they started up this college program to help blacks get into the University of Washington.
And they help get them jobs and they do all this stuff to get advisors form and all these things.
So, man, I took my SAT test and I did good on it. And September, I was at the University of Washington.
And now I'm a student there.
And now the movement all around us is really catching steam.
So, I get involved with some other black students there and we start the first black student union at the University of Washington.
So, we start the black student union and so all of us black students are meeting in the hub.
And, you know, Ron Dellum is coming up from Oakland and other organizers from San Francisco State.
Because they are, I started a big take over San Francisco State.
And so, then we helped to form a PSU in Garfield High School.
And so, you want to say a little bit about that?
Hi, honey.
So, ooh.
Who is this?
This is Telia, my granddaughter.
Well, you're now in the record of a wide-breed company.
So, anyway, so in our activity, we're getting politicized constantly.
You know, and I remember hearing about this organization in Oakland called the Black Panther Party that marks on the Capitol in Sacramento.
This was, I believe, in the summer of 1967, I believe it was before I even started school.
And so, anyway, you know, going through the PSU, we decided to have this demonstration in Franklin High School.
Because there's a racial incident that occurred there.
Plus, they don't have any black, any black or Asian staff on the school set.
So, we've had them.
Okay.
So, we can go on.
Okay, so, Franklin High School.
Yeah, so we go to Franklin High School.
We march on the school.
We march into the office.
Principal won't meet with us.
So, we march into his office and we're yelling and chanting it.
What was he saying?
Saying our chant.
Oh, it was the set of hiring a black staff.
Yeah.
And the incident that happened with the black student and the white student, they got in the fight.
The black student got kicked out.
The white student remained in school.
So, we wanted to address those two issues.
But he refused to meet with us.
And we marched into his office and we're yelling our chant.
So, he decides to leave the school.
And he tells us the staff to go home.
And so, the students are there.
And so, we get the students into the auditorium and we have a big rally.
And so, afterwards, we're feeling really like, yeah, man, we did something here.
We took over the school.
We ran them out of there.
So, we're feeling really good.
A week later, I get arrested from my home.
And along with other leaders of the demonstration.
And we're in the King County jail.
Charged with it.
Unlawful assembly.
The day is April 4th, 1968.
And Walter Concrite comes on announces Margaret the King is assassinated.
So, this was...
Yeah, we're in jail.
And then the riots are breaking out all across the country, even in Seattle.
And young people are going crazy.
And we want to be out there going crazy, but we can't.
So, I remember that evening going back to my bulk.
And saying to myself that they killed Margaret the King, a man of peace.
That now is time for something else.
And I decided that my picket sign was going to be replaced by a gun.
We had already had been doing some organizing with SNCC.
And we had met this guy named Brutu Man, who we're all going over there
to his house meeting.
And he had some guns over there.
And so, the idea had already been implanted in our heads, along with Stoke and Carmichael.
And others that armed violence was what was needed.
And did you look at in terms of self-defense or...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, whatever.
You know, whatever.
However, we...
I don't even think we had really even thought about it.
You know, we didn't know what we were going to do with the guns.
But it probably was more about self-defense, because we had seen a lot of police brutality that had been taking place.
So, you know, then in the backdrop you had, you know, Chagavera and Fidel Castro,
and then Marston, Havana, and the movie had just came out about Chagavera.
And you had the revolutionary movements that were taking place throughout South America,
Chile, Argentina, Brazil, and then as well as in Africa.
So, you know, all over the world, actually, you had this kind of uprising of young people,
you know, Europe and France, London, you know, even in India.
So, then you had the whole hippie movement, and the movement against the anti-war movement.
So, you know, it just seemed like, okay, America is just, you know, you're made to explode.
You know, people want to change.
And so, we finally got out of jail, and then I was ended up...
We went down to the Black Student Union Conference in San Francisco,
and while we were down there, we...
Bobby heard that Bobby sealed the leader of the Black Panther Party was coming to do the keynote address.
So, but we also heard that there was a funeral of this Panther who had been killed.
His name was Little Bobby Hutton. He was known as Little Bobby Hutton.
So, we went over to the funeral, and we had stopped and got some burrays before we went over there.
And we saw Marlon Brando standing out front with the Black...
...and the Jacket on the Black Burray talking with Bobby Seal.
We're going to the church.
Why did you stop to get the burrays?
Because that's what the Panthers wore, and we wanted to fit in, you know, we wanted to fit in.
And show solidarity.
And so, we...
We, you know, go in and see the body of Little Bobby Hutton.
It's a very emotional setting. His mother answered, wailing and crying and reaching out to his body.
And these Panthers are standing around the walls, you know, with their hands.
Arms folded, you know, looking very serious.
What were the circumstances of this?
He was, you know, it was because of Martin Luther King's death, you know.
And that there were some Panthers that wanted to take revenge, and they went out on the street.
And it wasn't something that was okay by the leadership, but it was some people that decided they wanted to do this on their own.
One of them was a leader in the party.
It was Elders Cleveland, David, L.U. too, as well.
Elders Huey and Bobby were in jail at the time.
Otherwise, they wouldn't allow this thing to happen.
So, they decided to go out on the street to, you know, try to do something.
They... getting a confrontation with some police to shoot out and soothe Little Bobby Hutton.
They would just leave her right into this abandoned house.
It's surrounded by police. They start shooting into the house.
You know, this goes on for, you know, 20, 30, 40 minutes to your gas.
And finally, you know, they have to surrender.
Little Bobby Hutton throws his rifle out the door, and they come out with their hands up.
Little Bobby Hutton is told to run towards a police car.
And he does, and they shoot him.
And you know, shoot him about 20, 25 times, you know.
And not only was Bobby Hutton killed, but Elders Peever was wounded.
And also put in jail, because he's an ex-fellon now.
And they're going to send him back to San Quentin.
David Hear you at the National Captain is also arrested.
And there's 18 other Panthers that are all arrested.
And another Panther that is wounded.
And these were early Panthers. These were early people.
And so now they're taken off the streets.
What's that got to say? Sound like an effort to just cut the Panther.
Yeah, it really had a devastating effect.
So that's what happened with Little Bobby Hutton.
And so Bobby Seale comes over later on that evening,
who knows he's very emotional.
He comes with Kathleen Cleaver and one of the wounded Panthers.
And he gives a speech that is very powerful, very emotionally charged.
And my brother and I, after the speech, along with Anthony,
where we make a B-line to where he's at.
And we tell him we want a Black Panther Party chapter in Seattle.
And so we played her.
She flies to Seattle.
Along with George Murray, the Minister of Education,
who was also a professor at San Francisco State College.
And was very much behind the big student strike they had there
for Black Studies program.
And how radical was the Black Student Union?
I'm going to construct as they invited him to be the keynote.
Yeah. Well, the thing is,
is that the Black Panther Party was such a powerful force
in the Bay Area and influencing force and a growing force
that you couldn't help but want to invite them.
Plus, there were people, and there were people at San Francisco State
who were in the Black Panther Party.
And there were a lot of the people who in the BSU
who associated and worked with the Black Panther Party.
You know, you had Emory Douglas, who was a Minister of Culture
of the Black Panther Party. He was a student there.
You know, George Murray, the Minister of Education,
was a professor there.
So that whole student strike,
the Black Panther Party had was one of the most key elements
in making that happen.
So Bobby Seal comes to Seattle with George Murray.
And there's about 20 people who all meet at my mother's house,
my parents' house. We meet over a two or three day period.
And, you know, a couple of people bring their guns to the meeting.
And so he tells us what you need to be in the Black Panther Party.
You know, he starts off that you need to have two weapons
and two thousand rounds ammunition.
And he also gives us a book, that's a 25 books,
that we're told we have to read.
And we have to read, study two hours a day
and have a little credit to casing class twice a week.
And he's on his way to the East Coast
to organize other chapters and branches.
He asked me to go with him.
But I wasn't ready to go.
You know, in the meeting he asked who's going to be the captain.
And it was, I was a dead thing as the captain.
So we started developing.
Were you up for that role or were you voted into it?
Or how was it you were?
I was kind of voted into it.
You know, everybody stopped pointing at me.
I don't know why, but they did.
So...
And you're 19 years old?
Yeah, 19.
And still a student that you do.
So a week later, I'm called to Oakland.
I'm called by the Civil College of Intelligence.
It has to come down.
It was my first flight on the airplane.
I had my black pants uniform on.
And I'm nervous about how I'm going to be accepted by these guys.
So at that point, what is the black pants uniform?
It's a black leather jacket, powder blue shirt with the black tie, black pants, black beret, and black shoes.
Or black combat boots.
And so that was a uniform.
A official uniform of the black pants, probably.
And that's part of the members.
We cried to wear most of the time.
And so, okay, I'm picked up for the airport by two pantas, Robert Bay,
who is a Vietnam veteran, along with Tommy Jones, who is also a veteran from the Navy.
And he's from Tacoma, Washington.
Robert Bay's a captain.
So I'm over to the office.
I meet the National Secretary.
And she tells me that Bobby Seal catch up with me in a couple of days.
And so I'm staying with Landon and Randy.
I'm staying with Tommy Jones.
But Robert Bay takes me to his house to meet Landon and Randy Williams, who are also captains.
They are Vietnam's Special Forces veterans.
And the first thing that they start wanting to show me was their weaponry.
And they each have their own armament in their rooms.
And they have bullet loading equipment.
And they're showing me their weapons and their handguns.
And so it's becoming clear that I'm in a serious organization with people that are really serious about what they're doing.
Did you handle the weaponry at that point in your life?
Yeah, growing up, we all had BB guns.
And we had 22s.
And we went hunting with 22s.
So yeah, and I'd handled a weapon at Voodoo Man's house.
And we had friends who did a lot of hunting.
And so they always had gun racks at their house.
And so guns were not foreign at all to me or us.
So I go to visit Huey and Jail.
That's one of the things I have to do is visit him.
I go out and sell papers with some Black Panther Party members.
And then I spent some time with Bobby Seale, traveling from Maricopa,
other meeting with BSU members.
And then we end up in San Francisco at a Central Committee meeting.
And at that meeting is Stokeley Carmichael, Don Cox, the Field Marshal of the Black Panther Party.
They will heal you to the National Captain.
And some other people, some other captains of the Black Panther.
And these guys are older guys.
And so I'm introduced as a new captain.
And then the next day I'm with Robert Bayland and in Randy and we're at the house.
We're drinking some, what is called, bitter dog, which was a street drink,
which is dark pork wine for a little bit out.
And you put some lemon juice in there.
You shake it out. It was pretty potent drink.
And later became known as Panther Piss.
It was dubbed Panther Piss. So we're drinking that.
We're smoking some brother Rugi, which is the code name for marijuana.
And Landon didn't drink or smoke weed, so he's in the front room watching TV.
So I'm getting it feeling no more comfortable and you know, loosening up and everything.
And suddenly we're here, a loud bang.
And we run into the living room and Landon is there with this 44 Magnum in his hand.
And Robert Bay says, man, what'd you do?
Man, why'd you shoot the TV out?
He said, I was tired of watching the Cowboys and Indians.
And the Indians always get killed. I shot the TV out.
And later on, right after that, we're going on to Seville Street in West Oakland.
We get something to eat.
And me and another young Panther named Orlando Harris, who was in Sacramento.
When they took the arm delegation, he's only 16 years old.
I think he was 15 when he went to Sacramento.
And he's very prominent in that film, holding an M1 car being with the toothpick in his mouth.
So me and him go out and we're smoking cigarettes and a car drives by police car.
He starts yelling at it.
Pig, you damn pig, you rest up at that stuff.
It's a cussing at the pig and he's just going off.
So I join in and I'm doing it too.
And this is only maybe two weeks after Little Bobby Hutton had been killed.
And there's a lot of tension, a lot of tension between the police department and the Black Panther Party.
And pretty soon the police goes around, he comes back and he calls for reinforcements.
More police start driving up on the scene.
The Robert Bay landing in a Randy come out in time with Jones, they come out.
And then people are actually running home and closing their stores and saying,
I'm getting out of here, it's going to be a shootout.
And this is the same corner that Huey Newton had his shootout,
he was wounded and two police were one was killed, one was wounded.
Same corner, seventh and wood.
So people are running, there's going to be, and people are pretty soon, the street is deserted almost.
And the prostitutes are the only ones that they're out there saying they're going to stay here and help see what happened to the panthers.
And I just remember Robert Bay comes out, he says spread out.
You know, he says spread out in this deep voice.
So we all spread out, the police are all bunched together.
The police have their hands on their guns.
And without so it's not to give them a bunch of targets.
Exactly, right. So we spread out, police, they don't spread out, they're all bunches up.
They're showing a lot more fear than we are.
They got their hands on their guns, we have our hands on our guns.
I had just been given a 9 millimeter automatic the day before.
And so we're all armed.
And I remember seeing a pretty soon the streets deserted.
So I'm thinking, oh shit man, what have I got myself into?
So I see this young black guy, he's got a bag of groceries.
And I'm sending myself, I wish he would stay here and help us.
And our eyes meet, and he looks at me and he says, man I would stay here and help you, but I got to get home.
And then he's gone.
And so now the police, there's a lieutenant out front of the police.
And he's looking at Landon, because Landon's out front of us.
And he's got his hand on his gun, he said, I'm going to search you.
And Landon says, no you're not going to search me.
And Landon, he starts walking towards Landon.
Landon starts backing up.
And I'm thinking shit Landon shot that TV out, shit.
You know what I'm telling him, what he's going to do.
So, and this went on for a few seconds, you know.
And it was so much tension, you could have cut it as cliché as it sounds.
But suddenly Landon tripped over a garbage can top.
He bounces right back up, but the garbage, you can hear the garbage can top reverberating.
And that just like cuts the tension.
Because the next thing, the police turn around.
They don't say a word, they turn around, they get in their cars and they drive off.
So, this was a victory for us.
You know, we stood our ground.
And they chose that this was not a night that they wanted to engage with us.
And so, we gave our guns to the prostitutes because we figured they're going to come back with more reinforcements.
And then finally we left and go home.
So, that was my baptism into the Black Panther Party that night.
And so, the very next day, they have the Saturday Panther meeting that they have every week at the St. Augustine's Church.
And so, panzers are coming from all over the Bay Area, San Mateo, San Jose, Richmond, Relayo, and everywhere.
There's about 125 people in there, you know, men and women.
You know, most people have the uniformed on.
And it's just electrifying.
And Bob Sierge gets up and he talks.
And he talks about the 10-point program.
We got to know the 10-point program and recite it.
And he introduces me.
And I met you, Duce, as a first captain of the Seattle Chapter.
First office outside of the state of California.
And so, after the meeting, you know, everybody's greeting me.
And, you know, I feel really like, you know, this is my new family.
And so, I leave with Robert Bay and Tommy Jones.
We go back to the house.
And when we get to the house, the phone rings.
Robert Bay runs and grabs the answer to the phone.
He said, yeah, he slammed the phone down.
He runs to his room.
He grabs two rifles.
He hands me one at a box of ammo.
And he says, the vampen on the camera is at the church.
So, we're jumping this car and he's speeding going about 50,
60 miles an hour down Gro street.
And they asked me if I know how to load the weapon.
And I said, yeah, I mean, I'd never seen that 40.
It was a 44-magnum car being.
But I figured out how to load it.
You know, so I load it.
And I'm saying, damn, here we go again.
So, we get down to the church.
There's nobody there.
And so, I don't know what happened or what the call was,
or if they left, but nobody's there.
So, we're relieved and nobody's there.
So, we're going back.
The next day, I'm on a flight back to Seattle.
So, I know what it is about to be in the Black Panther Party.
And so, I began, we began organizing the Seattle chapter.
And we opened up our first office and get our phones.
And take over 300 applications in over a month,
period of time, people wanting to join the Black Panther Party.
And...
That's going to say, I mean, they had to have the hot adrenaline
of these kind of things.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, that was just the beginning.
And that was just the beginning.
That was just the beginning.
You know, that was, oh my God.
So, anyway, you know, we open up our office.
We, you know, we've got all these young people and older people,
Vietnam, Bets, and the joining of everybody.
And we're carrying our guns around.
We're because it's not illegal to carry a gun down the street.
So, we're carrying our rifles, our shotguns, with us everywhere we go,
every up and down street in the cars.
These are all legally acquired guns.
They're legally acquired.
Well, I won't say they're all legally acquired.
They definitely weren't all legally acquired.
But they were legal guns.
They were automatic weapons.
Okay.
So, you know, then...
And to the police that were hassled you over?
Oh, yeah.
We're having confrontations continuously, you know,
as continuous confrontations.
And we started getting calls from the community
and we started getting domestic violent calls,
landlord disputes, problems with the police.
And, you know, we're trying to answer these calls.
And, you know, the domestic violence calls,
we'll send some armed pantas over there.
And they would, you know, stop that domestic violence that's going on.
It was really empowering.
And for the first time, the community had somebody they could call.
You know, for all kinds of problems.
And for the first time, they could just pick the phone up and say,
you know, hey, I got this problem.
I got that problem.
Will you send some people over here to help me?
You know, there was an incident where...
In America, we're talking about supposed to be the police.
But was that not the case?
Oh, no, it wasn't the case.
In Seattle or anywhere else, you know.
So, we now were filling that role.
So, there was a landlord incident where the landlord had taken the door off
of a hench of a woman who had seven kids.
And we sent some pantas to the house.
And they got the door and carried it down the street
and put it back on the woman's... on the henches.
So, we started getting calls from this high school.
We had a senior in week reports to Bobby Seal and we talked on the phone.
He told me, said, Dixon, you guys are going out on too many of these community calls
because the community likes to take advantage of you.
So, I want you to, you know, cut back on that.
What was your response to?
Right on, right on Chairman.
Right on Chairman Bobby, you know.
You know, we... you had to follow orders and all your actions.
That was one of the models of the Black Panther Party, all the orders and all your actions.
Now, we all doing your reading service.
We have a political education class.
We're having our red book.
You know, we studied the red book.
Chairman Miles Red books because it had a lot of things in there that were just basic common things.
You know, the three models and seven rules.
And just, you know, like you don't take anything from the people of the mass.
You turn everything, you borrow, you know, you fight against liberalism.
Criticism, constructive criticism and self-criticism.
And just all very basic things to help us, you know, with the day-to-day struggles and between ourselves and what we had to do.
As well as, you know, our political education class where we were, you know,
usually read out of the newspaper and discussed things that was in the Black Panther newspaper.
And so, you know, the Black Panther Party is spreading all across the country around this time.
And L.A. chapter is really catching a lot of, you know, three Panthers of Killed and L.A. and the Summer of 1968.
So, you read out some pretty heavy stuff.
Yeah, France for non-Bridge, other earths, Black Sea and White Mass, Black Rage and other things.
I mean, you know, even before that, we were already reading heavy stuff, you know, in college and even in high school.
We're, because there was a lot of Black writers who were writing a lot of, there was James Baldwin.
We always read a lot of James Baldwin, Richard Wright and many, many others.
You know, we were, we really read a lot even before we got into the party.
We were reading all these books.
But the folks that were being, that were applying to the membership and that were joining you.
Were they, were they down with this kind of reading? Or, you know, this is the whole thing with a lump in full eternity.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The lump in ready to read?
Well, yeah, yeah. I mean, people had the attempt through little education class.
People had to get the books. And, you know, Bobby Hutton didn't know how to read or write before he joined a party.
And by the time he's 17, he knows how to read and he knows how to write.
Because he's reading these things, you know, that he has to read and, and comrades help him with that as well.
So, and then we started getting a lot of college educated, college students that began to join the Black Rage experts.
So you got a combination of the lump in full eternity, and you got all these college students that are coming in as well.
So, it was a good combination of the two, you know, coming together.
So, so we started getting calls from this woman on Monday that her son was going to an all white high school.
He got beat up in the Prince of Wood doing thing about it.
So I explained her we couldn't come out there.
So she called back on Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday. Sorry, ma'am, we can't come.
She called back on Friday. She was crying towards the end of the school year. White students had bought bats and changed the school.
They were beating the kids and threatening the kids. Nobody were doing thing about it.
And so we got another call from another mother, same thing.
And so, when we got that last call, there were about 13 panthers in the office and everybody had their rifle and shotgun.
So I said, okay, let's go. We're going to go. So we get out there. There's 25 policemen there on the side of the building.
Already there. Already there.
Well, they might have been called out there because of the disturbance, because of what was going on.
Which hospital?
Rainer Beach.
By this time, school is already out.
So we cross the street. One of the sergeants says, Dixon, you can't take those loaded weapons into the school.
They don't know you at this point.
Yeah, they know they know me. They know, you know, they are the comrades.
And so knowing the gun laws and the gun law states it, if a bullet is not in the chamber and you're carrying it, then it is considered unloaded.
So they're not loaded. We go right into the office, into the school.
We see the principal. He sees us. He takes off running. We go back. That's how we get somebody.
They go get them and they escort them and sit them down and we tell them, you know, if you don't start protecting these kids, we're going to protect them.
And he is visibly shaken and he promises that for an hour, he will protect them.
And so we leave. We back our way across the street. We don't turn our backs to the police because that's one of the things he told me when I went to visit them.
They'll turn you back to the pigs.
We get in our cars and we drive back. They follow us back, but they don't stop us.
And they're trying to come up with some kind of indictment against us, but we didn't do anything illegal.
Right.
Because there's no law at that time against bringing rifle and shotguns into the school.
But that was the first major incident that really marked the emergence of the Seattle chapter.
Okay.
So, I mean, there's a lot of things that happened. I mean, I can't tell you everything.
You know, I would just say that we had some, there were some people who had joined the party for their own personal reasons.
And, you know, there were elements that were starting to do robbing banks and robbing stores that were connected to the party.
And, you know, the same thing happened, started happening in Oakland because a lot of these people, we didn't really have a way of providing income for people.
So, a lot of people, but in the Bay Area, just for a lot of people did, what they started, people who were from the lump and they started reverting back to their old tactic.
And the fact that they had a uniform on and a gun.
Because when you give young men a gun and you put a uniform on, they do crazy things.
And this was starting to happen within the party.
And then, would you try to control that?
Well, we had, what Huey did was, he, from prison, he gave an order that we had to have a purge.
So, we began to expel these people from the party, you know, and Oakland had a big purge in the Bay Area.
And, in Seattle, we had a big purge here as two.
And it really almost destroyed the party. There were two people that lost their lives behind this activity that was taking place.
It really damaged our credibility in the media, in the community.
And, you know, even people left because of that.
I know, particularly in Seattle, they were bombing instance.
Right, fire bomb.
Yeah, well, that was separate. That was separate from incident.
And that was separate because in July, after our return from New York was Bobby Seal and Elders Cleaver and Emory Douglas,
we went to the UN for the purpose of getting the UN to intervene in the trial of Huey Newton and intervene on the genocidal practices of the US against the Black community.
And so, it was a whole plan that the party had developed by going into the UN and having Black Panther Party members standing with free Huey flags
behind every flag of the United Nations.
And we were going to go in with the delegation of James Foreman, Stokeley Carmichael myself and so on.
But when we got to the SNCC office and had the meeting with James Foreman and Stokeley Carmichael, it ended up into a big argument.
And almost a fist fight. And we stormed out of the office and the coalition between SNCC and the Black Panther Party was dead at that point.
That was it. And James Foreman was the one that was supposed to get us into the UN.
So we had to find somebody else. We found this from a main Mallory who was one of the leaders, founders of the Black Power Movement.
And so we got a small audience with a 10th and near delegation.
This was June of 68.
Let's try to think in terms of when the former gets the Black manifesto.
Twitter met right around that same time.
Yeah, it probably was.
So you know, it was a power struggle because James Foreman, he had been around longer and he felt that because he had bought some of his field marshals up there to the meeting.
I mean, not to the meeting, but to be in the SNCC office while we were there.
And I just remember them not being very friendly and some tension going on there.
So, you know, I come back to Seattle and only a week after I've been in Seattle, the I'm on my way to the office.
And I see police cars in front of the office and I started to turn around.
I said, let me go find out what's going on. I go down there and ask me, are you here in Dixon? I said, yeah, there's your under arrest.
So I was arrested along with Curtis Harris and charged with stealing a typewriter.
Curtis Harris was the one that had been organizing these illegal activities and we didn't know what was going on at the time.
And then he later on would become suspected of being a police informer.
Because I was arrested, we were both arrested and he was released.
And they had a rally down at Garfield because the community heard about what happened until the party organized a big rally at Garfield High School.
And they marched down to the jail and you know demanded my freedom.
They marched back to Garfield and he ruptured into a riot, a major riot of Seattle's first major riot in the last three days.
And so there was a lot of fire bombing and turning over police cars.
At midnight they decided to let me go.
So they let me go at midnight and I picked up by some panthers.
Do they think of that, man?
Yeah, I thought they thought it would calm things down.
But I get out of midnight, there's still a rioting down at Garfield and they got the streets all blocked off and helicopter flying.
So I get to my mother's house and there's some panthers there.
It's about 8, 10, 12 panthers.
Everybody's got their rifles and guns and they want to go down to Garfield and you know engage the enemy.
And so you know they're trying to convince me and so you know I give in and say okay yeah let's go in and go down there.
So we try to make it down the foot.
Helicopter spots us and signs a light on us.
One of the panthers shoots the light out and pretty soon we know that the area is going to be surrounded by police.
It's somebody out there who we know he calls us into his house.
And just as we get into his house, the area is surrounded by police.
This kind of really kicks off kicks off a war between the Black Panther Party and the Seattle Police Department.
And so we go on a campaign of sniping and fire bombing.
And you know we're sniping at the police and pretty soon the Majority Hill we call it Portia.
It gets the name of Portchop Hill which is a Korean battle in Korea.
And police at night they don't come up there unless the three cars deep and with the four men in a car and the right shotguns hang out the window.
This is how tense it's gotten.
And so this goes on all through that whole summer of 68.
And all across the country you know you got people shooting at police you got riots you got people attacking police stations.
You know it's almost like the revolution had come that summer.
Did we ever reach out and try and negotiate with you or you know in a more peaceful way or was it just a situation?
No that wasn't going to happen because we weren't going to sit down and negotiate with them.
But the Seattle Metro did send a delegation up to meet with us because where our office was that's where the bus parked right in front of it.
And so when we open up our office we told the bus to out you can't park there you got to park back there.
And one day we were having a meeting and bus driver decided to test us.
He parked in front of us while we were having a political education meeting.
And Elmer and another Panther went on the bus and you know jumped on the bus driver took his phone out and threw it on top of the roof.
And I got charged with the potential charge so they had a war not for me.
And so I had to go down and turn myself in but the black judge had a black judge and he let me off.
But they did send a delegation down to meet with us to try and negotiate about letting them park their bus there.
And we told them no not while we were here.
And we needed to light lines out.
Yeah we needed to we didn't want our office blocked out because we had painted black Panther Party on there and Panthers on there.
And all the posters on our windows and everything.
So you know we survived that summer of 68 and then the fall you know first Panther is killed by the Seattle Police Department.
Well the Narpsets 17 years old.
What was the circumstances?
He was at home you know he was sort of like an underground and that he wasn't a full-time Panther but he bought money by and he bought guns.
He was still guns you know getting money.
He was a hustler but he was still a Panther.
He was a lump in proletariat you know.
So anyway he I guess the police were out looking for him.
He's at home at his mother's apartment and his him and his mother's apartment and up on the third floor.
He looks out the window he sees the police there confronting his mother and bothering his mother.
He grabs his rifle. He runs downstairs and he gets involved and they shoot him but they shoot him in the back.
And that was our first casualty.
And there was another casualty in December which came about because he was given an order by somebody to go rob a grocery store and the grocery store owned and killed him.
So that's when we started getting hit to you know something else is going on that we don't know about.
And so then my trial starts in December.
I have really a good lawyer this lawyer who eventually became a federal Supreme Court judge here in the state of Washington.
He was considered at the time to be one of the finest lawyers in the state of Washington.
He comes and volunteers take my case because what had happened was when we were trying to get all our things that we needed for our office typewriter,
desking all those things.
There was an informer that came into the party.
So this guy says hey man so and so is going to give us a typewriter down at the model city.
He said we can come down there after five while we got to do is going there and get it.
He'll leave the door open for us.
So I said okay let's go down there.
I was excited yeah we're going to get a brand new typewriter.
Excuse me so I carried it out.
I carried it out of there and I carried it into the office.
And a block away with the plane closed the tectas watching me carry it into the office.
The whole thing was a setup.
So when the trial comes there's a secret witness that they adjourn the hearing to wait for the secret witness.
So everybody's waiting for the secret witness.
Who is going to be the secret witness and he never shows up.
So I'm found not guilty.
I'm found not guilty so.
So anyway I end up going we end up having a purge.
We get rid of a lot of people and then we start the breakfast for school children program.
And there were people who didn't think that was revolutionary serving breakfast for school children.
We opened up our first breakfast program at Majorna Presbyterian Church.
That was in that was in the winter of 69.
Can I ask about the philosophy there?
So yeah this sort of maybe too competing camps is continuing our revolution or meeting basic needs in the community.
Talk a little bit about how that conversation was happening in the party.
Yeah are we ready?
Yeah we're ready.
And this was always this you know this was the the dual nature of the black Panther Party is that there were elements in the party that believed in arm guerrilla warfare.
And they wanted to go do that.
And Elders Cleaver was a chief proponent of that.
He is the one that caused that incident where little Bobby Hutton was killed.
And so there were you know people in the party who related to personalities.
There were people who loved the personality of you.
There are people who loved the personality of Bobby Sia.
And there are people who loved the personality of Elders.
And so they were willing to they thought that this was the way that we should be going.
So but anyway Elders has to go in exile you know and I think by 1970 he goes in exile.
And he goes from Cuba and then eventually is living in Algeria where we're the black Panther Party is given diplomatic status.
And as well as a diplomatic compound.
So you know and but this is still even though he's not in the country that still is still a continuing struggle in the party of you know community program.
So we go on and start many more community programs than the weatherman underground takes off.
And the East Coast Panthers.
And Bobby Seal is one of those who is a real proponent of a community program.
Yeah definitely.
Yeah.
And then so I go down to Oakland in 1969.
Bobby said I go down there and things aren't going well and Seattle.
Bobby Seal tells me to stay down there.
And so I stay down there and you know I go back down with my family and I'm you know getting training because this is what they instituted after I had become captain was a new chapters in branches.
They people had to come to Oakland and stay there for a while but they didn't happen with me because we were a new chapter.
So now I'm going to my kind of Panther training.
And I'm going to leave you in Oakland.
Elmer is running things and we had already started to purge before I went down there we had already purged Curtis Harris and a whole bunch of other people.
And so I told Elmer to just get rid of the rest.
Did that ever come back on you any of the purges of those people I imagine people weren't happy?
No, no, no, no, it didn't even come back and not necessarily.
I mean, yeah, I mean they were, my brother got threatened in Garfield high school.
Some of them came up there with guns and threatened him.
So, but you know they knew not to not to really mess with us.
So, when I'm down in Oakland, Bobby Seale gets kidnapped by the FBI and he's taken driven to Chicago by car.
Nobody knows where he's at.
And he goes through the whole Chicago trial.
They gag him, they chain him down to the chair.
And so David, here you take over the leadership of the party.
So, Eldritch is the next ex-Hewis in prison.
Bobby is now in jail.
And so the party is under attack.
FBI, a J.Kuhuver, they said that amongst themselves they were going to have us eliminated by 1969.
So, in January of 1969, Bunchy Carter and Eldritch John Huggins,
the two leaders of the Southern California chapter are assassinated.
Eleven months later, Fred Hampton, and his Chicago chapter is assassinated.
J.Kuhuver had sent out a memo that he wanted to check, three chapters destroyed,
Chicago, LA, and Seattle.
So, when Bobby is kidnapped and gone to jail, I'm sent back to Seattle.
We've got to start this campaign to try to free Seattle.
So, me and my brother, we start organizing the Seattle chapter.
We get orders to close down the storefronts and move into a community, move into a house in the communities that we find a duplex.
And we open up a community center in the duplex.
We start fortifying our office with sandbags.
Because we meet with this guy from the Justice Department of Black man, says he wants to meet with us.
We don't want to meet with him. We put it off. We put it off.
Finally, he says it's a matter of life and death. So, we meet with him.
He tells us that they're going to come in and kill us.
That they're going to raid us and kill us.
So, we start fortifying our office with sandbags and double sandbags and steal fortifications on the doors and on the windows.
Is he threatening you or is he threatening you?
No, he's not threatening me. He's tipping us off.
And what was motivated him, do you think?
He's black. And he's from Seattle.
And he tells us they're coming to kill you guys.
He really did tip us off.
So, we start preparing.
And we had already gotten orders anyway to fortify our offices.
So, all the Panther chapters all across the country are fortifying their office with sandbags and bunkers and all kinds of things.
And so, my brother and I, we're still students at the UDUB technically and we get our last financial aid checks, $1,700 each.
We spend our whole checks.
That whole all that money went on guns and munitions, gas masks, flat jackets and things that fortify our office, things that protect us.
That was the most important thing is that we're going to defend ourselves and protect ourselves.
But we had also started creating the breakfast program, then expanding the breakfast program, the five breakfast program locations in Seattle.
And Black Panther part of our cross the country is expanding these survival programs.
You know, we started the first three medical clinic in Seattle.
The party opens up 11 medical clinics all across the country.
And in some places they started a free ambulance program.
We started the first food bank program, you know, which is now a nationwide program and the state of Washington is a statewide program.
Black Panther Party, as far as the first food bank program, which is a staple now, the way that people survive and our clinics.
And so, we're a free legal aid program. We start a free legal aid program.
We start the bushing the prisons program. Somebody gives us a 35 passenger bus to use to go to all the prisons.
Then we're, you know, we're able to fund these programs.
We get orders that every Panther has to sell 100 papers a day.
So we're selling. So we got a lot of, some of the funds came from the newspaper.
But we had somebody who was a breakfast program coordinator, the medical clinic coordinator, the Liberation School coordinator.
And they had to go out and hustle. They had to go out and get money for their program to get resources for their programs.
Then there's wealthy people who, liberal who are donating money.
And we got a lot of money that was donated from Japanese, older Japanese.
And I didn't know why at the time, but I learned about the internment program.
That's why they were contributing to us.
So...
What's going on in your personal life right now? Are you still single or...?
Oh, I'd become married. And if 68 I got married, my son was born in 69.
So, you know, I got a little family going on.
So does that change things for you?
No, because my wife is in the party as well.
So, you know, it's just, you know, we're all just moving forward.
And, you know, like you said early on that, you know, you're going from these highs and lows.
We're really going through highs and lows now.
We're really going. It's just like everything is moving.
So, you know, we got to sell papers every day.
Everybody has to go on the field and sell papers every day.
Then we have, you know, the breakfast program.
We got to get up early in the morning, go to the breakfast program.
You know, we're running all these programs.
And no government funding is coming in.
But it's really a great time, you know, because, you know, we're so energized.
We're young. We got a lot of energy.
And we're able to do all these things.
And we're fairly. We're not afraid of anything, you know.
And so, it's just like 20 of us, 25 of us compared to 200 of us.
And we're doing so much work.
And not only do we have to do all this work, but when we come in from the field,
we all eat together communally.
And we have little graduation class.
We have weapon class.
And everybody has to pull security two hours a night, ten to twelve, two out of two, two to four, four to six.
So, you know, it's just constant thing.
It's very intense lifestyle, you know.
But, you know, we're, you know, this is what we want to do.
And so they began, so this attack, you know, this attack this guy is talking about.
And they start in Chicago.
They go in there. They kill Fred Hampton.
They try, they wanted to kill Bobby Rush, but he wasn't there.
And then four or five days later, they go to LA.
And they raid the LA office with the LA Panthers, a very military man.
They got a bunker built inside.
They never shoot out.
They're ready.
It has to six, eight hours, you know.
And the only thing that stopped them was they run out of ammunition.
And they surrender.
Then ATF comes to Seattle.
They go to Mara West Omen.
The Mara West Omen says, I'm not going to let you do that.
Because he saw what happened in Chicago.
He saw what happened in LA.
He said, it was a much smaller place.
Everybody knows us.
We are, we got, probably, as these programs, we got all these programs we're doing.
We're testing for sickle cell anemia.
We did the first mass testing of sickle cell anemia in Walla Walla, Peter Prison.
So, and me and people are depending upon us.
So how is he going to let the ATF come in there and try to kill us?
So he says no.
And so...
And you had any dealings with someone before this?
No, not really.
Not really.
But we had continuous attempts to raid our office by the Seattle Police Department.
And there were two policemen that they assigned just to harass us, arrest us.
And so, you know, it's been a constant battle just with the Seattle Police Department fighting them, you know.
And dealing with them and dealing with the issues that they're causing in the community as well.
Other black officers in the police are the...
There's only one.
Only one, yeah.
Yeah.
And he does intervene in the behalf of a panther Leon Valentine Hobbes.
So...
And so when Mara West all mistakes up,
then other municipalities start sticking up too and not allowing these raids to take place.
And when Mara...
West all men goes back to DC for the Mara's Convention.
These told he's not welcome.
And they don't let him in.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Because Nixon, you know, this is part of Nixon's plan.
He wanted...
This is what he wanted.
You know, I was on Nixon's enemy list.
He had an enemy list of 100.
I'm sure most of those people were panthers that were on that enemy list.
Seattle Police Department also put out a contract on my head at $25,000.
This was during the summer of 1968 to stop the fire bombing.
Because time magazine had a chart of cities during the summer of 1968.
They had two charts.
The chart of fire bombings and the chart of sniping.
And Seattle was number one on fire bombing compared to Chicago, Detroit,
and all the other places were number one.
And then we were number two in sniping.
So they felt that if they got rid of me, that they could in the fire bombing campaign.
And the fire bombing campaign was really directed at racist establishments, you know,
and outside of the community.
And you know, it got out of hand because there were some people who weren't
necessarily racist establishments that they did get fire bomb.
And that was casualties of war, you know.
But the targets chosen collectively.
Yeah, we chose targets collectively, but there were people who went off and did their own thing.
That was unfortunate.
So this guy Curtis Harris, this is during the summer of 1968.
I failed to mention this, but we got our hands on some dynamite.
And we left three, two people to watch the dynamite.
And we went somewhere and we came back and the dynamite was gone.
We said, we're going to have to the down.
All the police came in here and took it.
So we thought that was strange.
They were in police informants.
So about a couple of days later, these two police informants and Curtis Harris,
I'm closing office up one night and they said, we're going to Aaron, we're going to walk you home this summer.
68 when things are really hot.
And I thought that was unusual because they had never volunteered to walk me home before.
So you usually have security or bodyguards?
No, I didn't.
I didn't.
But there was one brother named Lou Jack, who said he was going to be my bodyguard.
And so he was with me quite a bit.
There was a story that he used to sleep in his car in front of my house.
But Lou Jack had become part of this other thing that was going on.
So anyway, these guys are going to walk me home.
They're going to walk me halfway there.
Police car drives by.
One of them pulls his gun out and shoots at the fire at the police.
And then I look around, they're gone.
They disappear.
And I knew that I better disappear.
So I'm trying to find somewhere to hide frantically.
And I run into the backyard.
And I said, damn, there's no escape from this backyard because it's got these high-wire bushes and fence are all way around.
So the police car is driving up.
I hear the police talking to themselves.
And then I hear them running up the stairs towards where I'm at.
And I pulled my gun out.
And I'm thinking, I'm dead.
A man comes out on the porch.
I knew the man.
I knew his kids.
I grew up with his kids.
He told his kids I had to hang around with me and my brother when we joined the party, which I can understand.
So he calls me and I run into his house.
And just there's a door close.
The police come into the yard.
And we're watching them.
They're searching.
And they go back out and they're looking under cars and they're looking under bushes and everything.
And so we wait and they leave.
And then after they left, I run home.
So anyway, getting back to what happened with Mayor West Omen.
So it also, it starts an investigation into not only the activities of the Black Panther Party, but also the response by the FBI.
And so because of this investigation, they have to stop those covert raids that they were doing on the Black Panther Party from 68 all the way to 69 where a lot of Panthers were arrested.
Many charged with long, long, many years in prison.
And so finally that kind of stops somewhat.
So then we're moving forward our programs.
And then in 70, I think it was about 71.
In the fall of 71, me and another Conrad, we decided to take our weapons out.
All the weapons, we get them all together and put them in his step van.
We're going to take them out and test them.
So we take them all out and we're testing them.
We test all the weapons itself for the last one, which was a shotgun.
I had a riot 18 shotgun that I purchased in Oakland and a band that attached me on it.
And I had my own bandit layer of shells that I used.
And you know, my bandit layer oftentimes was in the office and everybody knew that was my bandit layer.
So big Malcolm says, Aaron, this is your weapon. You go in fire.
And we have been smoking some hash on the way there.
I put the shutter shotgun up to my shoulder.
Something tells me don't fire it for my shoulder.
I bring it down here, fire from here.
As soon as the firing pin hits the primer, the gun explodes.
And you know, blows my arm halfway off.
So I got all this.
And I got steel rod and two plates on my arm.
And you know, I go through about four surgeries.
But we had the bullets tested and found out that the gunpowder had been taken out.
And high explosives had been put in its place.
So it was definitely another assassination attempt.
So when I was back in the office within three days, you know, with my arm cast.
Because we just had too much work to do here.
If that guy had been up out of her height.
Yeah, I'm going to blew my head.
I wouldn't be here.
So and shortly after that, there's a split between the black panther part.
That's when the split happens.
Because he we get released from prison.
And there's a lot of high hopes.
And then him and Eldridge get on a, you know, a talk show.
Letters have been sent to Eldridge in Algeria.
They're saying he wants to kill you.
They've been letters sent to Huey saying, Eldridge wants to kill you.
So they were FBI was fostering already the strain relationships and the distance that they had between each other.
And so and the New York panthers decide that they want to take orders from the weather underground.
And they feel that the underground movement is where it's at.
Huey exfels them from the black panther party.
And that leads to the split into the party.
And so.
And how are you hearing about these things?
I'm getting, you know, calls from National Hickory.
I'm called down there.
I get called down there.
We're another panther officials from all across the country are called down the open.
And we're, you know, we're told about the situation.
And they want to see who side everybody is on.
And, you know, most of New Jersey and New York go with Eldridge.
And just about everybody else.
Except for the Samson system.
Not some of the Samson system panthers who are real close to Eldridge.
They go with Eldridge.
And the Berkeley panthers, they go with Eldridge as well.
And so now, you know, we're, you know, we're fighting each other, you know, on the streets.
And people get killed.
And Huey decides not to have this thing get escalated anymore.
You know, he could have sent, he could have given the order.
And we could have had a all out war.
But Huey says, no, you know, we're not going to go that way.
So, you decide to, you know, Oakland is going to be a base of operations that we need to have a base.
And we need to strengthen that base.
And so, as a centralization campaign, it started panthers of all from all over the country to Oakland, to be stationed in Oakland.
Elmer had gone to jail, to prison in Oregon for our robbery of a leather coat.
So when the centralization takes place, you know, he's locked up.
So we leave a skeleton crew of people in Seattle.
And before that, before we went down to Oakland, we had let a campaign to get Elmer free.
We actually got the governor to pardon him.
Because that's the first time and only time that happened that a governor was going to pardon the black man as a party member.
But myself and my father and my attorney, we met with the governor.
And we got him to do this.
And we had a petition drive as well.
So we all come down to Oakland as people there from all over the country.
I come down with my wife and my son.
I must have been about 10 to 15 of us.
And we had so well established in Seattle.
But Elmer was able to come out and recruit new people.
And they were able to keep the clinic going and expand the clinic and expand the programs and really keep things going.
And then Oakland, we decided we were going to enter the electoral process.
You know, the first thing we did is support Shirley Chisholm's campaign for president.
And we began our organizing our own campaign, the Rumbabis Silver Mayor of Oakland, Lane Brown, the City Council.
Open up five campaign offices.
It's a massive four campaign.
We give away 10,000 bags of groceries with the chicken in every bag as to kick off the campaign at the Oakland Auditorium.
And I just remember seeing the bags 10,000 empty bags on the floor of the Oakland Auditorium.
And how we were able to make this thing happen.
You know, put the chickens in the eggs and potatoes in the can food, loaf of bread, and give it out so that the chicken is still frozen the very next day.
And it was just a beautiful campaign.
I was confined to the office as officer of the day.
I thought I was going to get a high level position in the campaign, but I didn't.
He really was trying to get rid of me.
He had gotten rid of other people, and he was trying to get rid of me.
People would ask me, asked if I'd be included in the security squad that he had set up.
He had chosen people from different places to be in this security squad.
And there were people that felt that I should be in, but he would always say no.
So what do you think was going on there?
He thought I had too much power.
I was a threat to him, because he felt that he told somebody that a lot of people had a lot of respect for me in the party.
And so he was doing that with some really good people.
He ran off a lot of really good people.
Eventually we ran, you know, we ran by this campaign.
It was a massive campaign.
We didn't win, but we came really close.
And so other politicians started coming to us, because they saw we had a political machine.
We couldn't get out the vote.
We really did. We put 350 people out on the street every day to get people, to register people to vote.
And the campaign, we put four or five hundred people out on the street.
We took people out of the homes to the polling places.
So we did truly have a political campaign.
Did there were black folks registered or were voting in these days?
No, they weren't. We met so many people that never voted before and opened.
Old people never voted, never even registered the vote.
So that was a very important piece to get these people registered and get them involved in the campaign.
And these visitors, things on voting day to make sure that people got there.
Yeah, we had people standing on corners and freeway overpasses that we had vans going to people's homes,
taking people from the homes to the polling places.
So we were very much active that whole day, you know, that whole day.
So, in terms of, you know, I don't know how much I'm worried.
I'm just curious about how much, I don't know how much you're thinking these things through,
but, you know, from armed revolution to actually using, you know, the political system.
And this is a different kind of tactic.
Yeah, well see, that was the beauty of about the Black Panther Party,
is that we were netted, never wedded to one tactic, you know.
And because we read a lot, we understood that nothing stood outside of change,
that we always had to be adaptable.
And we always had to be changing, you know, that's why we went from, you know,
the armed revolution to the breakfast program, the survival program,
and doing all these programs, and then to the electoral politics,
we were constantly evolving and constantly changing our tactics to achieve, you know,
what we were trying to achieve.
And so, and you know, there was always people on the left who always criticizes
for, first of all, having the broad coalitions that we had with all the different people.
And, you know, with the Brown Berets, the Red Guard, the AIM,
the white, the young patriots and SDS,
a piece of freedom party, and then now the survival program, you know,
most revolutionary organizations at that time,
they didn't think about doing those survival programs, you know, feeding kids,
and you know, they didn't think that was revolution, but it was very revolutionary.
And so, then we went from there, and we went to the electoral politics, you know,
and it just made perfect sense that, you know, we would try to take over the whole
electoral piece of Oakland.
That's what was our goal to make Oakland a base of our operations and expand from there.
It's about changing the system, so we have valor from what we have to do.
And we could do it with both. But we still had our underground.
We still had a...
This was actually before the split, after the split, the underground cave then,
because there were people who were in the underground who sided with elders,
and they no longer had the support from the party.
One of those people was Geronimo, he was kind of caught in the middle,
and he had a case, and he and Panthers were allowed to testify in this case,
so he goes to prison.
So, anyway, then he will become starting cocaine,
and his whole piece about what he's supposed to be doing,
and what the party is supposed to be doing really gets distorted,
and he really begins to become more of a gangster than a revolutionary.
So you see his personality really starts to change?
Yeah, cocaine has really changed.
Plus, the fact that when he went to prison,
the Black Panther Party was just a small organization based in Oakland and in LA.
Now, you know, just friends, people he knew, now he comes out as an international organization.
He's an international hero.
He's almost on the level of Chagavera, you know,
and he's got access to all this power and money,
but he also...
There's all these people he doesn't know, and he doesn't trust him, you know.
And we're paranoid, anyway, we're already paranoid.
We're paranoid about the phone, we're paranoid about so-and-so,
we're working next to us, and who's an informant, who's not an informant?
And so then, you know, he comes out and he's paranoid,
and then he starts not at cocaine, he becomes even more paranoid.
And I think at some point he really didn't realize,
he didn't want to...
This is not really what he wanted to do.
You know, this is not what the role that he envisioned himself doing.
He was thrusted up into this role, you know?
And so he starts dismantling the party.
So anyway, our contract is put on on his head.
A warrant is also put on on his head.
You know, he runs off Bobby Seal, John Seal, many other people,
and he has to go and flee and go to Cuba and go into exile.
And Lane Brown becomes the chairperson of the Black Panther Party.
And so she starts rebuilding the party, and she chooses me as her bodyguard.
Can you ask this as a service, I've barred,
if you could talk about the role of women in the party and how women...
Well, if that were treated, what the philosophy of the party was in terms of including women?
Yeah. Well, women were considered to be equal in the party.
They did everything that the men did, and they weren't confined to doing women's chores.
And first of all, the type of women that joined the party,
they weren't going to go for that anyway.
They were some very tough, very demanding women.
You know, you couldn't pull no crap off over on them.
And so they were equal, and they served in leadership.
The Connecticut chapter was run by a woman.
Erica, again, the Boston chapter, Captain was a woman, Audrey Jones.
And so you had Panthers, women who were a Lane Brown,
Kathleen Cleaver on the Central Committee of the Black Panther Party.
So women had a very prominent, very strong role in the party.
Now, that doesn't just say that there weren't problems that existed,
because trying to overcome the whole issue of male dominance in machoism and stuff,
was very difficult.
And there were places, in some places, in the Southern California chapter,
where women were abused, you know, in many ways.
And so that's where the Lane Brown had come out of.
Now, here she was, was ahead of the whole Black Panther Party,
of what was left of it.
So she began to rebuild the party.
I'm on her bodyguard.
Yeah, and she goes to Cuba, and Huey tells her to visit Huey,
and Huey tells her to ask Lina Wilson,
a retired superior court judge, if he wanted to be mayor.
And so we asked him, and he said, yeah,
and so we start running a campaign to run him from mayor.
Namin Wau.
You asked the question, don't you?
You know what Alexander?
Yes.
Yeah.
Tell me something about her, she's an old friend.
Oh, wow, wow.
Bertha Alexander, man.
If this tall woman, right?
Yeah, kind of like conflicted, yeah.
And she worked a lot with big man,
and big man was the editor of the newspaper,
and they traveled, they did a lot of traveling around the world,
you know, talking about where they went to Japan.
They spent a lot of time in Japan, in South Korea,
and many other places.
And she worked on the newspaper too.
She was a very, you know, very important person, you know, in the party.
Yeah.
She's still alive?
She's still alive.
Where she is?
She's in California, so I'm not sure if you can watch Android.
I'll be there.
A little self-aware.
Okay.
She isn't, she isn't, um,
she's in my way with dance classes together.
There were roommates in the whole of Japan.
Wow.
But yeah, you tell me you ran into him again.
Yeah.
So, um, well, I'm glad you did.
I'm so glad to hear that she's alive and doing well.
Yeah, damn.
So anyway, uh...
Is that sort of given, I guess, to the world?
No.
Love people are...
Actually, no, it's not, it's not a given, especially some women.
Because they had, they did have a hard time with some things.
But so did a lot of men, you know, and so it just wasn't easy, you know, after it was all over.
But getting back to the story, when we, uh, before we ran Lionel Wilson's campaign,
Jerry Brown came to us and asked us to support his mayor for, uh, his bid for governor at the state of California.
And he had some, uh, close relationships with party members in LA and Elaine Brown knew him.
So we said, yeah, yeah, we'll support you.
We'll work in your campaign.
So, uh, Lauren, they already become the governor.
And so Elaine is, is spending a lot of time in the governor's office meeting with him.
And Tony Klein, who was a head legal person in the state of California,
and then also worked with the party in Southern California.
So, um, uh, and Elaine is cultivating this relationship.
Um, Jerry Brown calls Elaine up and says, I have six judgeships that I want to fill in the, in Oakland.
Can you help me? She says, yes, I'll give, give, give back with you with the name.
She gives them the name of six black attorneys, and they all become judges.
And so you could say that we had some control of the judiciary in Oakland because of this.
And those lawyers knew why they became, uh, judges.
It was because of the black Panther Party.
Elaine made sure they understood that.
So, you know, damn, you know, we got some, we got some power here, you know.
So there, then we started running Liner Wilson's campaign.
And Lauren Behold, we put the first black mayor into office in Oakland.
And then we turned, he's going to point two Panther women to the port of Oakland.
And this, the Central Committee has made up of mostly women at this time.
Uh, because Elaine, you know, bought women up and got them on the Central Committee.
And so now we're in Liner Wilson's office.
We're running the city.
Oh, the black Panther Party is running the city.
We're meeting with the, uh, the, um, yeah, what is that person's name?
I can't think it was a name.
But, uh, man, it was, it was, it was really sent.
Plus we had a private school in a community center.
And the private school was one of the best private schools in the country.
It started off as a private school just for Panther kids, but expanded to the community.
We had people who were doctors and lawyers that had their kids there, as well as kids who came from the housing projects that were students there.
We had a Marshaar's program.
It was, uh, on the cover of Black Belt Magazine, it had over 100 students.
We had, um, we started the first gang intervention program in the Bay Area.
And we got a Cedar Grant, you know, Cedar was the comprehensive employment program.
That was one of the best programs the government ever had.
Uh, they gave money to nonprofits and businesses to hire people.
And so we, we were able to put 20 Panthers on, on the payroll with, with the big Cedar Grant that we got.
And that's how we started our gang intervention program.
And then we started a, a seniors against a fearful environment program where we got gang members.
We hired gang involved youth to, uh, work with seniors on the weekends when they got to paycheck and escort them to the bank, escort them to the grocery store and so on.
So, um, and Elaine was able to clean the image up of the Black Panther Party.
We also had a restaurant, a bar in Grille in downtown Oakland called the Lamp Post.
We also had, um, a, you know, some other businesses.
We had a promotion business where we bought Marvin Gaye and Chakka Khan and Earth Wind and Fire and other people to Oakland.
And I continued to turn around with didn't turn out to be so good.
Um, and so, you know, um, and then we had these millionaires who all they did was give money to the party.
And so we were, have bought a lot of property.
We owned a lot of property, you know, where we had the school was a huge property.
What about your lunch? We only have a couple of things of the nation.
And, you know, the island of President Sinnoh Klan and property have businesses.
I mean, the nation of Islam.
We had a contentious relationship with them because Huey was, um, when he, before he went into exile, he was, um, was involved in drug operation, you know.
And, um, he had actually told Farrakhan, they had a meeting with Farrakhan that, you know, you stay over in San Francisco and we'll deal with Oakland.
And, uh, Huey didn't like heroin.
He would not allow heroin. He didn't like heroin to be on the streets.
But because, uh, Cokin was a casual drug.
It was something that he had gotten, the party had gotten involved in, and working with, uh, different drug dealers and after our clubs and stuff.
And, also, uh, making the after-hour clubs and the pimps pay the party.
They had to pay money. That's why Huey had to go into, uh, because that's why they put this contract on.
Because he, he, he, he had, uh, instituted a policy where they had to pay money to the party in order to operate.
And so he had gotten...
And so, and so...
And we had, Arkansas, actually had a, uh, a movie theater that we were, uh, got from the, uh, Mafia, the Mafia on this, uh, Oakland theater.
And we were, we were putting on, uh, we, we were running it and we were showing movies there.
So, there was a lot of stuff going on.
Yeah.
We were in the polls, but...
Okay.
So, Oakland, uh, Elaine is becoming like really well-known.
And she's, she's the most powerful person in the state of California.
You know, Leo McCarthy, the, uh, the speaker of the house for the state assembly.
Uh, Willie Brown, you know, I met all these guys.
If we were down in Sacramento all the time and going to these events with, with these big, high guys and...
It just fawning all over Elaine, you know, that, that one thing they're afraid of or the other thing they have great respect for.
Mm-hmm.
Elaine's also cultivating relationships with the big corporations.
The Shedderly, William Shedderly had a, uh,
Clark's corporation, or, you know, one of those corporate, a couple of those corporate.
I mean, she could go to these people and say, I need $400,000 for the school and they'll give it to her.
So, we got a lot of power.
Yeah.
Now, is the Panther image changing at all?
I'm exterior-wise, I'm gonna say we'll still wear the uniform.
No, we're wearing suits, and we're wearing suits.
You know, this, in 1969, we stopped wearing, we got orders to stop wearing the, the Panther uniform,
because it separated us from the community and made us targets.
So, we had already started dressing differently, you know, in 1969.
And so, but now, you know, you know, those of us, we're running the school.
We've got a private school.
We're running all this big nonprofit entity.
We've got about four or five different nonprofits.
And we, you know, we got these businesses we're running.
Mm-hmm.
And, um, and so, you know, and Elaine is very much in, you know,
the whole image mold.
So, you know, people who are around the year to be well dressed.
Mm-hmm.
And, um, and so, Elaine becomes president of the Oakland Redevelopment Corporation
that wants to redevelop downtown Oakland.
And, and, and because Oakland is, is kind of been suppressed.
So, she's now over all these millions of dollars to develop Oakland.
Mm-hmm.
And as part of this, she makes them put it in there that they have to build
1,000 low income housing units for this redevelopment.
But, in order to make this happen, they need the freeway to come through Oakland.
Mm-hmm.
And so, she's able to get, uh, Jerry Brown to release the funds to build the freeway ramps
that come into Oakland, you know.
And so, you know, that's okay.
And so, that, that starts to happen.
And so, Elaine has become a very powerful person in Oakland.
Mm-hmm.
I mean, in, in, in the state of California, she could get almost anything she wants
from these politicians, because they're afraid of her from what.
And, and she's extremely intelligent and extremely bright.
Mm-hmm.
So, she pays the way for Huey to come back and, and stand trial.
And, uh, that was the fate of a mistake.
Because our goal was we had taken over Oakland.
Okay, so we were going to do the same thing in other parts of the country.
We're going to do it in Seattle.
We're going to do it in Chicago.
We're going to do it in other places where there was still a Black Panther Party networks.
And, um, and, uh, so, um, so she pays the way for Huey to come back to stand trial.
And, um, and she comes back and, you know, first of all,
she sees all the power she has.
And, uh, he wants control of that money she has as well.
Mm-hmm.
And she's, she's not giving that up.
She's not going to do that.
And, uh, some other things happen.
He starts back, starting cocaine again.
There was a, uh, a drug gang that had been, uh, terrorizing one of the,
actually had taken over a housing project near the school.
And so, uh, we had started a campaign to get rid of this, uh, drug gang.
And, uh, these guys had machine guns.
They had, uh, the whole shabang, you know, um, and they were, I think they were getting the hair on from the Mafia.
They were very well organized.
They even had, were using a computer back then.
And so, so we're planning against them, you know, we're, you know, we hit a couple of their safe houses.
We're organized in community against them.
Mm-hmm.
And, um, and they...
It's really at the beginning of gangs getting into the...
Yeah, this was the beginning.
And Felix Mitchell, the guy's name is Felix Mitchell.
And this is going to be, this is going to be bloody.
It is going to be a lot of people going to be killed in this.
Uh-huh.
Uh, cause they're driving by the school and they're looking at us.
They're looking at me and Elaine's car.
They're stopping and writing things down.
And we're doing the same to them.
And so, uh, then he comes back.
He comes back.
He wants control of this money.
He lane won't give it to him.
He does some other things.
He forces Elaine out the party, lane these party.
And she takes out a full pay page ad and the whole contribute.
Uh, you know, she says that she's going to pursue her music career
cause she's been under contract in Motown
cause she made several albums while she was in the party.
And so, um, and then when she leaves,
and a lot of these very smart women start leaving.
Now is there a relationship to this drug...
The story you're certainly telling about the drug gang and the...
Yeah.
Because in Huey comes back and when Elaine leaves,
he meets with these two drug gangs and tells them that
in order to operate that they got to pay the party, you know,
25,000, 50,000 a week or a month or something like that.
And so they go, they said they don't think about it.
And so we start preparing, you know, to go to war with these guys.
Um, and then, and also, um,
Huey, at this point everything he does is wrong.
Everything he does just leads to a quicker decline of the party, you know.
He decides that this woman who is could testify against him in the trial,
Elaine already had that on the control.
She already had gotten somebody to become good friends with this woman
and follow her around and become close with her.
And, uh, as to try to find out what she's going to say during the testimony,
but Huey decides he wants to have her eliminated.
And he sends some people to have her.
Now I suppose it would be one of those people,
but he has me replaced at the last minute.
The person he replaces me with, when they get to the scene,
they accidentally shoot another panther in the back of the head
and everything just falls apart from there.
They got to leave this guy's body there.
And so the next day, the Oakland Tribune Panther and
Lou Jopsooth found with M-16, you know,
and they found another M-16 and it just spirals downhill from there.
And that really was pretty much the end of the Black Panther Party.
The last thing I did, I got orders to,
Huey's trying to cover his tracks, these people going underground,
because the congressional investigation has been convened to investigate
the Black Panther Party and all these things that have been happening.
And I get this note order to get rid of all the weaponry,
ill-legal weaponry of the party.
And so I spend two days crawling in crawl spaces,
digging up weapons, going in addicts,
and collecting all these weapons, machine guns,
50 caliber machine guns, anti-aircraft weapons, M-16s,
AK-47, you know, all these weapons that we accumulated over the years.
And I have to dump it off to a Marin County,
the Marin Bridge, you know, at three in the morning.
I had to make two trips.
I got the longest U-Haul truck you could get.
It took me two days, and even then, when I thought I was finished,
I get back to my house, and I'm laying across it bed,
and I'm looking to cross it, and there's about four M-16s in the closet.
So I got to take those down, I go throw them in the open estuary.
And I get in a confrontation with Bill Cosby,
I'm passing out some flyers for a Huey's upcoming trial.
and he talks about Huey.
And I have no defense for Huey,
because everything he says is true.
And about a week later, after that,
I leave the Black Panther Party,
then I meet someone who was in the party,
who leaves as well, and he says,
it's a good thing you left the theory,
it was going to have you kill.
So I left just in time,
which always seemed to be one step ahead
of whatever danger was coming.
When you say, what did that mean to leave the party,
or what did that entail you?
Well, you know, for most people, when people left the party,
they left, and they didn't tell nobody.
They left at night.
They didn't take anything with them,
but maybe they're bare essentials.
They just left in the middle of the night.
But I didn't feel that I wasn't going to leave that way.
I had been ten years, I had given everything I had,
I wasn't going to leave like that.
Now I told Big Bob, Huey's bodyguard,
that I wanted to take a leave of absence for a year.
He called Huey and got Huey to okay it,
and then I left.
Did you ever expect to live that long?
Oh, no, none of us ever expected to live very long at all,
because there were over 30 party members that were killed
from 67 to about 1972.
So no, I never expected to live.
None of us expected to live to be too long.
So then after you left did you come back up to Seattle?
No, I didn't, because I couldn't leave Oakland.
I had too many memories here.
I was tied there.
Even though I got in the threat from Huey,
when I helped somebody else to leave,
when I took another panther to the airport to go to LA to leave,
and Huey found out about it and had Big Bob call me and tell me,
I had 24 hours to leave town.
Even then I still didn't leave.
I just, you know, hid out in San Francisco
and just, you know, was careful where I went and what I did.
And then that situation just cooled down?
Yeah, because the party was going down.
You know, people were leaving and pretty soon there was,
you know, people were leaving.
So, so I, I could have had, came back,
my father would come and get me a job at Boeing.
The parents would come back and go to school at the UW.
But I had been on the other side for so long that I just couldn't do it.
I couldn't see myself going from what I had done,
been doing to now, going to college.
You know, I had been on the other side of the law for so long.
And I had that adrenaline brush.
I had become addicted to it.
And I tried to get a job, I, you know, got some jobs
and it didn't work out.
And I met some people and I got involved in the criminal life.
And, you know, for a year I was involved in,
I sold some cocaine and I got involved in bezel-mountain.
Made a hundred thousand dollars in the year and went on the run
from the FBI for about a year.
And eventually, you know, it was caught and came back to Oakland
and got out and, you know, started, you know,
putting my life together and, you know, worked.
And you served time over that?
I did. I served about a year, about a year.
And became a substance abuse counselor.
And, you know, eventually I did move back to Seattle.
So I guess we start to wrap up,
but tell me about the kinds of work that you then went into.
Back in the hall.
It's a school. It is, I was sorry.
Thank you. Thank you.
The kinds of work that you ended up doing back then.
Well, you know, at first I started off as a substance abuse counselor
in Oakland and I did that for a while.
And I was, I did really good at it,
even though I had never abused substances before.
And that was when I first started,
I started working at, I added, first the detox and we started,
opened up a big, uh,
uh, living, uh, recovery program.
And these guys said,
and you said, man, you ain't never been no drug addict.
Well, how are you going to teach us anything?
But I just had that natural way of empathizing with people.
And I became the best counselor on the staff.
And I even bought in some of the things that we had done in the Black
Friends program where I helped them open up a,
a clothing program or then in the thing and doing some other thing.
And, um, I had an evaluation that I had to do
and I had to go down and meet with the executive director.
And the executive director was,
he had a degree, he was a doctor,
he was over the West Open Health Clinic.
And he was also a doctor at several hospitals.
And he hired everybody that came in and he fired everybody.
So it was like this control, he was a control dude, you know.
And he had a big giant house in Sonoma County and all this stuff.
So I go in to see him for my evaluation.
And he said to me,
he's sitting in his big leather chair and he says to me,
Dixon, I hear you've been fucking up.
I said, I just, I said, man, fuck you.
Kiss my mother fucking ass and walked out, you know.
Because I, I've been to that shit with somebody else with Huey.
I wasn't gonna go through that with nobody else.
So I walked off the job.
And I was able to get on the firm.
They fought tooth and nail to keep me from getting on the plane.
I was told, man, nobody ever gets on the planet from these people.
But I was able to get it.
And so I went up to Northern California,
worked on a marijuana farm for a couple of months
and had people selling marijuana for me.
Eventually I came back to Seattle
because what happened was the crack cocaine epidemic hit.
And that's what my next book is gonna be about.
It's gonna be what happened in the 80s
and how all that cocaine came in
and how it affected the black community.
I saw what it did to Oakland.
It was just like a wave or black cloud.
It was, Oakland was such a vibrant place in the 70s for black people.
We called it Chocolate City.
We had a black mayor with black nightclubs and ill, man.
It was just a great place to be than all of a sudden this thing hit.
And I saw it hit.
And I had friends and party members who were addicted to cocaine.
And everybody else was selling it and teachers.
And everybody, man, it was just a mess.
So I came back to Seattle.
A month after I've been to Seattle,
here comes the epidemic in Seattle.
And I bought my girlfriend from Seattle with me.
She was addicted to cocaine.
I didn't know it.
And so we had two kids.
And I was trying to keep her from being addicted.
And you can never do that.
And so I struggled with that and became a gang counselor,
worked with youths.
And that's a whole another story,
which I'm gonna talk about in my second book.
What are you doing now?
Well, I started a nonprofit organization about 10 years ago.
And we opened up a transition housing program for 18 to 24 years.
And we started youth leadership project in high school.
We went five different schools.
We started the first media literacy program in a high school here in Seattle.
We took a group of kids to the world,
such a farm in Brazil on several occasions.
And I got burnt out on that.
And finally got my book finished.
And I got behind paying my federal income taxes for the nonprofit.
I wasn't a good administrator.
And towards the end, I really was really tired of doing that.
I really wanted to write.
And so in August, I became separated from Central House.
The transition house is still going on.
But I got separated from that.
Which was, you know, I was able to get unemployment.
I filed for my Social Security.
And in September, I had a big book opening for my book.
My book came out in September 17th.
And I went on a book tour.
So one thing replaced the other.
So in July, I'm gonna start working on my second book.
But you've been going around with the book.
And I just were talking to a lot of people.
There's a lot of young people that have a lot of questions.
And they're really hungry.
How did you do it?
And how were you able to sacrifice yourself so selflessly?
And how do we stop police brutality?
How do we do this? How do we do that?
I was gonna say, because some of the...
I was gonna ask you about the legacy of your work.
Because some of the I know, like, the health clinic survives.
But then the same issues are used to you, especially with the police brutality.
And it works.
Things are much, much worse.
Because we don't have the unity that we had.
We don't have the unity among black people.
We don't have the unity that we had as people, working class people,
working class people that we had back then.
Oh, you were describing it.
Yeah, you know, individualism.
Start getting pushed in the 1970s,
and, you know, narcissism is very much a part of our culture now.
And this whole individualism and materialism that really, you know,
Ronald Reagan really kicked off with that neo-economic policies
and deregulation is this really has taken this country down the drain.
Not the fact, mentioned the fact that he was responsible along with George Bush for
flying in all those shipments of cocaine that devastated the black community.
Not only devastated the black community, but it's affected the whole economy of America
because all the resources that have had to go to dealing with that crisis.
And now we have two and a half million people in prison.
Most of them, six percent of my Latino and black males, the crack cocaine addiction
really has devastated the black community.
It just destroyed our families, destroyed our community.
We don't have community anymore.
We don't have the type of family structures that we have anymore.
We have kids raising themselves, the cultural value system that we have when we're growing
up does not exist anymore.
Because we had a cultural value system that existed prior to 1970s and 80s.
You know?
I grew up up with two parents and family.
And people stayed together.
Even though they didn't get along, they stayed together for the family.
That was the most important thing, whether they got along together or not.
And you don't see that kind of sacrifice and commitment anymore.
So let me just ask you if there's anything else or anything I didn't ask about or anything
else that you thought I should have asked or that you would like to say to Ralph?
No, that's about it.
That's about it.
I came back to Seattle two weeks ago because I had five events up there up here that I
had to go to.
So I've been talking, oh man, I've been really busy.
Every day this past week I've had an even speaking event that I've had to go to.
And I bought Elaine Brown up here on Thursday along with Cha Cha Jimenez from the Young
Lords.
And we had a nice big event at the University of Washington which was really, there was
a well-attended packed audience and it was really turned out to be a really great event.
Is your still touch with the way I live?
Oh yeah, yeah.
Elaine and her good friends.
She came to my book event and opened up on with Erica Huggins.
This has been a presentation of the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian National Museum
of African American History and Culture.